<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html
PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en">
<head>
<title>Chapter Three</title>
<link rel="stylesheet" href="en-bg.css" type="text/css" />
</head>
<body>
<div class="book-title">Bhagavad-gītā As It Is</div>
<div class="chapter-head">Karma-yoga</div>
<div class="canto">[Ch.</div>
<div class="chapter">CHAPTER THREE</div>
<div class="image2">
<img src="images/bg-logo.gif" alt="Bhagavad-gita As It Is" />
</div>
<div class="ch-title">Karma-yoga</div>
<div class="ch-number">3</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text1" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 1</strong></div>
<div class="dev-uvaca">@jauRna ovaAca</div>
<div class="devanagari">jyaAyas$aI caetk(maRNAstae mataA bauiÜ"jaRnaAdR"na /<br />taitkM( k(maRiNA GaAere" maAM inayaAejayais$a ke(zAva // 1 //</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans-uvaca">arjuna uvāca</div>
<div class="sans">jyāyasī cet karmaṇas te<br />matā buddhir janārdana<br />tat kiṁ karmaṇi ghore māṁ<br />niyojayasi keśava</div>
<div class="wbw"><em>arjunaḥ uvāca</em>&nbsp;– Arjuna said; <em>jyāyasī</em>&nbsp;– better; <em>cet</em>&nbsp;– if; <em>karmaṇaḥ</em>&nbsp;– than fruitive action; <em>te</em>&nbsp;– by You; <em>matā</em>&nbsp;– is considered; <em>buddhiḥ</em>&nbsp;– intelligence; <em>janārdana</em>&nbsp;– O Kṛṣṇa; <em>tat</em>&nbsp;– therefore; <em>kim</em>&nbsp;– why; <em>karmaṇi</em>&nbsp;– in action; <em>ghore</em>&nbsp;– ghastly; <em>mām</em>&nbsp;– me; <em>niyojayasi</em>&nbsp;– You are engaging; <em>keśava</em>&nbsp;– O Kṛṣṇa.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Arjuna said: O Janārdana, O Keśava, why do You want to engage me in this ghastly warfare, if You think that intelligence is better than fruitive work?</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The Supreme Personality of Godhead Śrī Kṛṣṇa has very elaborately described the constitution of the soul in the previous chapter, with a view to delivering His intimate friend Arjuna from the ocean of material grief. And the path of realization has been recommended: <em>buddhi-yoga,</em> or Kṛṣṇa consciousness. Sometimes Kṛṣṇa consciousness is misunderstood to be inertia, and one with such a misunderstanding often withdraws to a secluded place to become fully Kṛṣṇa conscious by chanting the holy name of Lord Kṛṣṇa. But without being trained in the philosophy of Kṛṣṇa consciousness, it is not advisable to chant the holy name of Kṛṣṇa in a secluded place, where one may acquire only cheap adoration from the innocent public. Arjuna also thought of Kṛṣṇa consciousness or <em>buddhi-yoga,</em> or intelligence in spiritual advancement of knowledge, as something like retirement from active life and the practice of penance and austerity at a secluded place. In other words, he wanted to skillfully avoid the ﬁghting by using Kṛṣṇa consciousness as an excuse. But as a sincere student, he placed the matter before his master and questioned Kṛṣṇa as to his best course of action. In answer, Lord Kṛṣṇa elaborately explained <em>karma-yoga,</em> or work in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, in this Third Chapter.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text2" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 2</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">vyaAima™aeNAeva vaAfyaena bauiÜM" maAeh"yas$aIva mae /<br />tade"kM( vad" inaiêtya yaena ™aeyaAe'h"maA«auyaAma, // 2 //</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>vyāmiśreṇeva vākyena<br />buddhiṁ mohayasīva me<br />tad ekaṁ vada niścitya<br />yena śreyo ’ham āpnuyām</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>vyāmiśreṇa</em>&nbsp;– by equivocal; <em>iva</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>vākyena</em>&nbsp;– words; <em>buddhim</em>&nbsp;– intelligence; <em>mohayasi</em>&nbsp;– You are bewildering; <em>iva</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>me</em>&nbsp;– my; <em>tat</em>&nbsp;– therefore; <em>ekam</em>&nbsp;– only one; <em>vada</em>&nbsp;– please tell; <em>niścitya</em>&nbsp;– ascertaining; <em>yena</em>&nbsp;– by which; <em>śreyaḥ</em>&nbsp;– real beneﬁt; <em>aham</em>&nbsp;– I; <em>āpnuyām</em>&nbsp;– may have.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>My intelligence is bewildered by Your equivocal instructions. Therefore, please tell me decisively which will be most beneﬁcial for me.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">In the previous chapter, as a prelude to the <em>Bhagavad-gītā,</em> many different paths were explained, such as <em>sāṅkhya-yoga, buddhi-yoga,</em> control of the senses by intelligence, work without fruitive desire, and the position of the neophyte. This was all presented unsystematically. A more organized outline of the path would be necessary for action and understanding. Arjuna, therefore, wanted to clear up these apparently confusing matters so that any common man could accept them without misinterpretation. Although Kṛṣṇa had no intention of confusing Arjuna by any jugglery of words, Arjuna could not follow the process of Kṛṣṇa consciousness&nbsp;– either by inertia or by active service. In other words, by his questions he is clearing the path of Kṛṣṇa consciousness for all students who seriously want to understand the mystery of the <em>Bhagavad-gītā.</em></div>
<div class="text-number" id="text3" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 3</strong></div>
<div class="dev-uvaca">™aIBagAvaAnauvaAca</div>
<div class="devanagari">laAeke('ismainã"ivaDaA inaï"A paur"A ‘aAe·(A mayaAnaGa /<br />ÁaAnayaAegAena s$aAÊÿYaAnaAM k(maRyaAegAena yaAeigAnaAma, // 3 //</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans-uvaca">śrī-bhagavān uvāca</div>
<div class="sans">loke ’smin dvi-vidhā niṣṭhā<br />purā proktā mayānagha<br />jñāna-yogena sāṅkhyānāṁ<br />karma-yogena yoginām</div>
<div class="wbw"><em>śrī-bhagavān uvāca</em>&nbsp;– the Supreme Personality of Godhead said; <em>loke</em>&nbsp;– in the world; <em>asmin</em>&nbsp;– this; <em>dvi-vidhā</em>&nbsp;– two kinds of; <em>niṣṭhā</em>&nbsp;– faith; <em>purā</em>&nbsp;– formerly; <em>proktā</em>&nbsp;– were said; <em>mayā</em>&nbsp;– by Me; <em>anagha</em>&nbsp;– O sinless one; <em>jñāna-yogena</em>&nbsp;– by the linking process of knowledge; <em>sāṅkhyānām</em>&nbsp;– of the empiric philosophers; <em>karma-yogena</em>&nbsp;– by the linking process of devotion; <em>yoginām</em>&nbsp;– of the devotees.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>The Supreme Personality of Godhead said: O sinless Arjuna, I have already explained that there are two classes of men who try to realize the self. Some are inclined to understand it by empirical, philosophical speculation, and others by devotional service.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">In the Second Chapter, verse 39, the Lord explained two kinds of procedures&nbsp;– namely <em>sāṅkhya-yoga</em> and <em>karma-yoga,</em> or <em>buddhi-yoga.</em> In this verse, the Lord explains the same more clearly. <em>Sāṅkhya-yoga,</em> or the analytical study of the nature of spirit and matter, is the subject matter for persons who are inclined to speculate and understand things by experimental knowledge and philosophy. The other class of men work in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, as it is explained in the sixty-first verse of the Second Chapter. The Lord has explained, also in the thirty-ninth verse, that by working by the principles of <em>buddhi-yoga,</em> or Kṛṣṇa consciousness, one can be relieved from the bonds of action; and, furthermore, there is no ﬂaw in the process. The same principle is more clearly explained in the sixty-first verse&nbsp;– that this <em>buddhi-yoga</em> is to depend entirely on the Supreme (or more speciﬁcally, on Kṛṣṇa), and in this way all the senses can be brought under control very easily. Therefore, both the <em>yogas</em> are interdependent, as religion and philosophy. Religion without philosophy is sentiment, or sometimes fanaticism, while philosophy without religion is mental speculation. The ultimate goal is Kṛṣṇa, because the philosophers who are also sincerely searching after the Absolute Truth come in the end to Kṛṣṇa consciousness. This is also stated in the <em>Bhagavad-gītā.</em> The whole process is to understand the real position of the self in relation to the Superself. The indirect process is philosophical speculation, by which, gradually, one may come to the point of Kṛṣṇa consciousness; and the other process is directly connecting everything with Kṛṣṇa in Kṛṣṇa consciousness. Of these two, the path of Kṛṣṇa consciousness is better because it does not depend on purifying the senses by a philosophical process. Kṛṣṇa consciousness is itself the purifying process, and by the direct method of devotional service it is simultaneously easy and sublime.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text4" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 4</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">na k(maRNAAmanaAr"mBaAªaESk(mya&lt; pauç&amp;SaAe'´autae /<br />na ca s$aªyas$anaAde"va is$aiÜM" s$amaiDagAcC$ita // 4 //</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>na karmaṇām anārambhān<br />naiṣkarmyaṁ puruṣo ’śnute<br />na ca sannyasanād eva<br />siddhiṁ samadhigacchati</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>na</em>&nbsp;– not; <em>karmaṇām</em>&nbsp;– of prescribed duties; <em>anārambhāt</em>&nbsp;– by nonperformance; <em>naiṣkarmyam</em>&nbsp;– freedom from reaction; <em>puruṣaḥ</em>&nbsp;– a man; <em>aśnute</em>&nbsp;– achieves; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– nor; <em>ca</em>&nbsp;– also; <em>sannyasanāt</em>&nbsp;– by renunciation; <em>eva</em>&nbsp;– simply; <em>siddhim</em>&nbsp;– success; <em>samadhigacchati</em>&nbsp;– attains.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Not by merely abstaining from work can one achieve freedom from reaction, nor by renunciation alone can one attain perfection.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The renounced order of life can be accepted when one has been puriﬁed by the discharge of the prescribed form of duties which are laid down just to purify the hearts of materialistic men. Without puriﬁcation, one cannot attain success by abruptly adopting the fourth order of life (<em>sannyāsa</em>). According to the empirical philosophers, simply by adopting <em>sannyāsa,</em> or retiring from fruitive activities, one at once becomes as good as Nārāyaṇa. But Lord Kṛṣṇa does not approve this principle. Without puriﬁcation of heart, <em>sannyāsa</em> is simply a disturbance to the social order. On the other hand, if someone takes to the transcendental service of the Lord, even without discharging his prescribed duties, whatever he may be able to advance in the cause is accepted by the Lord (<em>buddhi-yoga</em>). <em>Sv-alpam apy asya dharmasya trāyate mahato bhayāt.</em> Even a slight performance of such a principle enables one to overcome great difﬁculties.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text5" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 5</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">na ih" k(iêtºaNAmaipa jaAtau itaï"tyak(maRk{(ta, /<br />k(AyaRtae ÷vazA: k(maR s$avaR: ‘ak{(itajaEgAuRNAE: // 5 //</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>na hi kaścit kṣaṇam api<br />jātu tiṣṭhaty akarma-kṛt<br />kāryate hy avaśaḥ karma<br />sarvaḥ prakṛti-jair guṇaiḥ</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>na</em>&nbsp;– nor; <em>hi</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>kaścit</em>&nbsp;– anyone; <em>kṣaṇam</em>&nbsp;– a moment; <em>api</em>&nbsp;– also; <em>jātu</em>&nbsp;– at any time; <em>tiṣṭhati</em>&nbsp;– remains; <em>akarma-kṛt</em>&nbsp;– without doing something; <em>kāryate</em>&nbsp;– is forced to do; <em>hi</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>avaśaḥ</em>&nbsp;– helplessly; <em>karma</em>&nbsp;– work; <em>sarvaḥ</em>&nbsp;– all; <em>prakṛti-jaiḥ</em>&nbsp;– born of the modes of material nature; <em>guṇaiḥ</em>&nbsp;– by the qualities.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Everyone is forced to act helplessly according to the qualities he has acquired from the modes of material nature; therefore no one can refrain from doing something, not even for a moment.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">It is not a question of embodied life, but it is the nature of the soul to be always active. Without the presence of the spirit soul, the material body cannot move. The body is only a dead vehicle to be worked by the spirit soul, which is always active and cannot stop even for a moment. As such, the spirit soul has to be engaged in the good work of Kṛṣṇa consciousness, otherwise it will be engaged in occupations dictated by the illusory energy. In contact with material energy, the spirit soul acquires material modes, and to purify the soul from such afﬁnities it is necessary to engage in the prescribed duties enjoined in the <em>śāstras.</em> But if the soul is engaged in his natural function of Kṛṣṇa consciousness, whatever he is able to do is good for him. The <em>Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam</em> (1.5.17) afﬁrms this:</div>
<div class="verse-in-purp"><em>tyaktvā sva-dharmaṁ caraṇāmbujaṁ harer<br />bhajann apakvo ’tha patet tato yadi<br />yatra kva vābhadram abhūd amuṣya kiṁ<br />ko vārtha āpto ’bhajatāṁ sva-dharmataḥ</em></div>
<div class="purp">“If someone takes to Kṛṣṇa consciousness, even though he may not follow the prescribed duties in the <em>śāstras</em> or execute the devotional service properly, and even though he may fall down from the standard, there is no loss or evil for him. But if he carries out all the injunctions for puriﬁcation in the <em>śāstras,</em> what does it avail him if he is not Kṛṣṇa conscious?” So the puriﬁcatory process is necessary for reaching this point of Kṛṣṇa consciousness. Therefore, <em>sannyāsa,</em> or any puriﬁcatory process, is to help reach the ultimate goal of becoming Kṛṣṇa conscious, without which everything is considered a failure.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text6" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 6</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">k(maeRin‰"yaAiNA s$aMyamya ya @Astae manas$aA smar"na, /<br />win‰"yaATaARna, ivamaUX#AtmaA imaTyaAcaAr": s$a ocyatae // 6 //</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>karmendriyāṇi saṁyamya<br />ya āste manasā smaran<br />indriyārthān vimūḍhātmā<br />mithyācāraḥ sa ucyate</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>karma-indriyāṇi</em>&nbsp;– the ﬁve working sense organs; <em>saṁyamya</em>&nbsp;– controlling; <em>yaḥ</em>&nbsp;– anyone who; <em>āste</em>&nbsp;– remains; <em>manasā</em>&nbsp;– by the mind; <em>smaran</em>&nbsp;– thinking of; <em>indriya-arthān</em>&nbsp;– sense objects; <em>vimūḍha</em>&nbsp;– foolish; <em>ātmā</em>&nbsp;– soul; <em>mithyā-ācāraḥ</em>&nbsp;– pretender; <em>saḥ</em>&nbsp;– he; <em>ucyate</em>&nbsp;– is called.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>One who restrains the senses of action but whose mind dwells on sense objects certainly deludes himself and is called a pretender.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">There are many pretenders who refuse to work in Kṛṣṇa consciousness but make a show of meditation, while actually dwelling within the mind upon sense enjoyment. Such pretenders may also speak on dry philosophy in order to bluff sophisticated followers, but according to this verse these are the greatest cheaters. For sense enjoyment one can act in any capacity of the social order, but if one follows the rules and regulations of his particular status, he can make gradual progress in purifying his existence. But he who makes a show of being a <em>yogī</em> while actually searching for the objects of sense gratiﬁcation must be called the greatest cheater, even though he sometimes speaks of philosophy. His knowledge has no value, because the effects of such a sinful man’s knowledge are taken away by the illusory energy of the Lord. Such a pretender’s mind is always impure, and therefore his show of yogic meditation has no value whatsoever.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text7" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 7</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">yaistvain‰"yaAiNA manas$aA inayamyaAr"Batae'jauRna /<br />k(maeRin‰"yaE: k(maRyaAegAmas$a·(: s$a ivaizASyatae // 7 //</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>yas tv indriyāṇi manasā<br />niyamyārabhate ’rjuna<br />karmendriyaiḥ karma-yogam<br />asaktaḥ sa viśiṣyate</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>yaḥ</em>&nbsp;– one who; <em>tu</em>&nbsp;– but; <em>indriyāṇi</em>&nbsp;– the senses; <em>manasā</em>&nbsp;– by the mind; <em>niyamya</em>&nbsp;– regulating; <em>ārabhate</em>&nbsp;– begins; <em>arjuna</em>&nbsp;– O Arjuna; <em>karma-indriyaiḥ</em>&nbsp;– by the active sense organs; <em>karma-yogam</em>&nbsp;– devotion; <em>asaktaḥ</em>&nbsp;– without attachment; <em>saḥ</em>&nbsp;– he; <em>viśiṣyate</em>&nbsp;– is by far the better.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>On the other hand, if a sincere person tries to control the active senses by the mind and begins karma-yoga [in Kṛṣṇa consciousness] without attachment, he is by far superior.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">Instead of becoming a pseudo transcendentalist for the sake of wanton living and sense enjoyment, it is far better to remain in one’s own business and execute the purpose of life, which is to get free from material bondage and enter into the kingdom of God. The prime <em>svārtha-gati,</em> or goal of self-interest, is to reach Viṣṇu. The whole institution of <em>varṇa</em> and <em>āśrama</em> is designed to help us reach this goal of life. A householder can also reach this destination by regulated service in Kṛṣṇa consciousness. For self-realization, one can live a controlled life, as prescribed in the <em>śāstras,</em> and continue carrying out his business without attachment, and in that way make progress. A sincere person who follows this method is far better situated than the false pretender who adopts show-bottle spiritualism to cheat the innocent public. A sincere sweeper in the street is far better than the charlatan meditator who meditates only for the sake of making a living.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text8" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 8</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">inayataM ku(ç&amp; k(maR tvaM k(maR jyaAyaAe ÷k(maRNA: /<br />zAr"Ir"yaA‡aAipa ca tae na ‘ais$aDyaed"k(maRNA: // 8 //</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>niyataṁ kuru karma tvaṁ<br />karma jyāyo hy akarmaṇaḥ<br />śarīra-yātrāpi ca te<br />na prasidhyed akarmaṇaḥ</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>niyatam</em>&nbsp;– prescribed; <em>kuru</em>&nbsp;– do; <em>karma</em>&nbsp;– duties; <em>tvam</em>&nbsp;– you; <em>karma</em>&nbsp;– work; <em>jyāyaḥ</em>&nbsp;– better; <em>hi</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>akarmaṇaḥ</em>&nbsp;– than no work; <em>śarīra</em>&nbsp;– bodily; <em>yātrā</em>&nbsp;– maintenance; <em>api</em>&nbsp;– even; <em>ca</em>&nbsp;– also; <em>te</em>&nbsp;– your; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– never; <em>prasidhyet</em>&nbsp;– is effected; <em>akarmaṇaḥ</em>&nbsp;– without work.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Perform your prescribed duty, for doing so is better than not working. One cannot even maintain one’s physical body without work.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">There are many pseudo meditators who misrepresent themselves as belonging to high parentage, and great professional men who falsely pose that they have sacriﬁced everything for the sake of advancement in spiritual life. Lord Kṛṣṇa did not want Arjuna to become a pretender. Rather, the Lord desired that Arjuna perform his prescribed duties as set forth for <em>kṣatriyas.</em> Arjuna was a householder and a military general, and therefore it was better for him to remain as such and perform his religious duties as prescribed for the householder <em>kṣatriya.</em> Such activities gradually cleanse the heart of a mundane man and free him from material contamination. So-called renunciation for the purpose of maintenance is never approved by the Lord, nor by any religious scripture. After all, one has to maintain one’s body and soul together by some work. Work should not be given up capriciously, without puriﬁcation of materialistic propensities. Anyone who is in the material world is certainly possessed of the impure propensity for lording it over material nature, or, in other words, for sense gratiﬁcation. Such polluted propensities have to be cleared. Without doing so, through prescribed duties, one should never attempt to become a so-called transcendentalist, renouncing work and living at the cost of others.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text9" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 9</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">yaÁaATaARtk(maRNAAe'nya‡a laAek(Ae'yaM k(maRbanDana: /<br />tad"Ta&lt; k(maR k(AEntaeya mau·(s$aËÿ: s$amaAcar" // 9 //</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>yajñārthāt karmaṇo ’nyatra<br />loko ’yaṁ karma-bandhanaḥ<br />tad-arthaṁ karma kaunteya<br />mukta-saṅgaḥ samācara</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>yajña-arthāt</em>&nbsp;– done only for the sake of Yajña, or Viṣṇu; <em>karmaṇaḥ</em>&nbsp;– than work; <em>anyatra</em>&nbsp;– otherwise; <em>lokaḥ</em>&nbsp;– world; <em>ayam</em>&nbsp;– this; <em>karma-bandhanaḥ</em>&nbsp;– bondage by work; <em>tat</em>&nbsp;– of Him; <em>artham</em>&nbsp;– for the sake; <em>karma</em>&nbsp;– work; <em>kaunteya</em>&nbsp;– O son of Kuntī; <em>mukta-saṅgaḥ</em>&nbsp;– liberated from association; <em>samācara</em>&nbsp;– do perfectly.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Work done as a sacriﬁce for Viṣṇu has to be performed; otherwise work causes bondage in this material world. Therefore, O son of Kuntī, perform your prescribed duties for His satisfaction, and in that way you will always remain free from bondage.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">Since one has to work even for the simple maintenance of the body, the prescribed duties for a particular social position and quality are so made that that purpose can be fulﬁlled. <em>Yajña</em> means Lord Viṣṇu, or sacriﬁcial performances. All sacriﬁcial performances also are meant for the satisfaction of Lord Viṣṇu. The <em>Vedas</em> enjoin: <em>yajño vai viṣṇuḥ.</em> In other words, the same purpose is served whether one performs prescribed <em>yajñas</em> or directly serves Lord Viṣṇu. Kṛṣṇa consciousness is therefore performance of <em>yajña</em> as it is prescribed in this verse. The <em>varṇāśrama</em> institution also aims at satisfying Lord Viṣṇu. <em>Varṇāśramācāravatā puruṣeṇa paraḥ pumān/ viṣṇur ārādhyate</em> (<em>Viṣṇu Purāṇa</em> 3.8.8).</div>
<div class="para">Therefore one has to work for the satisfaction of Viṣṇu. Any other work done in this material world will be a cause of bondage, for both good and evil work have their reactions, and any reaction binds the performer. Therefore, one has to work in Kṛṣṇa consciousness to satisfy Kṛṣṇa (or Viṣṇu); and while performing such activities one is in a liberated stage. This is the great art of doing work, and in the beginning this process requires very expert guidance. One should therefore act very diligently, under the expert guidance of a devotee of Lord Kṛṣṇa, or under the direct instruction of Lord Kṛṣṇa Himself (under whom Arjuna had the opportunity to work). Nothing should be performed for sense gratiﬁcation, but everything should be done for the satisfaction of Kṛṣṇa. This practice will not only save one from the reaction of work, but also gradually elevate one to transcendental loving service of the Lord, which alone can raise one to the kingdom of God.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text10" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 10</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">s$ah"yaÁaA: ‘ajaA: s$a{"î"A paur"AevaAca ‘ajaApaita: /<br />@naena ‘as$aivaSyaDvamaeSa vaAe'istvaí"k(AmaDauk,( //10//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>saha-yajñāḥ prajāḥ sṛṣṭvā<br />purovāca prajāpatiḥ<br />anena prasaviṣyadhvam<br />eṣa vo ’stv iṣṭa-kāma-dhuk</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>saha</em>&nbsp;– along with; <em>yajñāḥ</em>&nbsp;– sacriﬁces; <em>prajāḥ</em>&nbsp;– generations; <em>sṛṣṭvā</em>&nbsp;– creating; <em>purā</em>&nbsp;– anciently; <em>uvāca</em>&nbsp;– said; <em>prajā-patiḥ</em>&nbsp;– the Lord of creatures; <em>anena</em>&nbsp;– by this; <em>prasaviṣyadhvam</em>&nbsp;– be more and more prosperous; <em>eṣaḥ</em>&nbsp;– this; <em>vaḥ</em>&nbsp;– your; <em>astu</em>&nbsp;– let it be; <em>iṣṭa</em>&nbsp;– of all desirable things; <em>kāma-dhuk</em>&nbsp;– bestower.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>In the beginning of creation, the Lord of all creatures sent forth generations of men and demigods, along with sacriﬁces for Viṣṇu, and blessed them by saying, “Be thou happy by this yajña [sacriﬁce] because its performance will bestow upon you everything desirable for living happily and achieving liberation.”</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The material creation by the Lord of creatures (Viṣṇu) is a chance offered to the conditioned souls to come back home&nbsp;– back to Godhead. All living entities within the material creation are conditioned by material nature because of their forgetfulness of their relationship to Viṣṇu, or Kṛṣṇa, the Supreme Personality of Godhead. The Vedic principles are to help us understand this eternal relation, as it is stated in the <em>Bhagavad-gītā: vedaiś ca sarvair aham eva vedyaḥ.</em> The Lord says that the purpose of the <em>Vedas</em> is to understand Him. In the Vedic hymns it is said: <em>patiṁ viśvasyātmeśvaram.</em> Therefore, the Lord of the living entities is the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Viṣṇu. In the <em>Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam</em> also (2.4.20) Śrīla Śukadeva Gosvāmī describes the Lord as <em>pati</em> in so many ways:</div>
<div class="verse-in-purp"><em>śriyaḥ patir yajña-patiḥ prajā-patir<br />dhiyāṁ patir loka-patir dharā-patiḥ<br />patir gatiś cāndhaka-vṛṣṇi-sātvatāṁ<br />prasīdatāṁ me bhagavān satāṁ patiḥ</em></div>
<div class="purp">The <em>prajā-pati</em> is Lord Viṣṇu, and He is the Lord of all living creatures, all worlds, and all beauties, and the protector of everyone. The Lord created this material world to enable the conditioned souls to learn how to perform <em>yajñas</em> (sacriﬁces) for the satisfaction of Viṣṇu, so that while in the material world they can live very comfortably without anxiety, and after ﬁnishing the present material body they can enter into the kingdom of God. That is the whole program for the conditioned soul. By performance of <em>yajña,</em> the conditioned souls gradually become Kṛṣṇa conscious and become godly in all respects. In the Age of Kali, the <em>saṅkīrtana-yajña</em> (the chanting of the names of God) is recommended by the Vedic scriptures, and this transcendental system was introduced by Lord Caitanya for the deliverance of all men in this age. <em>Saṅkīrtana-yajña</em> and Kṛṣṇa consciousness go well together. Lord Kṛṣṇa in His devotional form (as Lord Caitanya) is mentioned in the <em>Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam</em> (11.5.32) as follows, with special reference to the <em>saṅkīrtana-yajña:</em></div>
<div class="verse-in-purp"><em>kṛṣṇa-varṇaṁ tviṣākṛṣṇaṁ<br />sāṅgopāṅgāstra-pārṣadam<br />yajñaiḥ saṅkīrtana-prāyair<br />yajanti hi su-medhasaḥ</em></div>
<div class="purp">“In this Age of Kali, people who are endowed with sufﬁcient intelligence will worship the Lord, who is accompanied by His associates, by performance of <em>saṅkīrtana-yajña.</em>” Other <em>yajñas</em> prescribed in the Vedic literatures are not easy to perform in this Age of Kali, but the <em>saṅkīrtana-yajña</em> is easy and sublime for all purposes, as recommended in <em>Bhagavad-gītā</em> also (9.14).</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text11" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 11</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">de"vaAna, BaAvayataAnaena tae de"vaA BaAvayantau va: /<br />par"s$parM" BaAvayanta: ™aeya: par"mavaApsyaTa //11//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>devān bhāvayatānena<br />te devā bhāvayantu vaḥ<br />parasparaṁ bhāvayantaḥ<br />śreyaḥ param avāpsyatha</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>devān</em>&nbsp;– demigods; <em>bhāvayatā</em>&nbsp;– having pleased; <em>anena</em>&nbsp;– by this sacriﬁce; <em>te</em>&nbsp;– those; <em>devāḥ</em>&nbsp;– demigods; <em>bhāvayantu</em>&nbsp;– will please; <em>vaḥ</em>&nbsp;– you; <em>parasparam</em>&nbsp;– mutually; <em>bhāvayantaḥ</em>&nbsp;– pleasing one another; <em>śreyaḥ</em>&nbsp;– benediction; <em>param</em>&nbsp;– the supreme; <em>avāpsyatha</em>&nbsp;– you will achieve.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>The demigods, being pleased by sacriﬁces, will also please you, and thus, by cooperation between men and demigods, prosperity will reign for all.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The demigods are empowered administrators of material affairs. The supply of air, light, water and all other benedictions for maintaining the body and soul of every living entity is entrusted to the demigods, who are innumerable assistants in different parts of the body of the Supreme Personality of Godhead. Their pleasures and displeasures are dependent on the performance of <em>yajñas</em> by the human being. Some of the <em>yajñas</em> are meant to satisfy particular demigods; but even in so doing, Lord Viṣṇu is worshiped in all <em>yajñas</em> as the chief beneﬁciary. It is stated also in the <em>Bhagavad-gītā</em> that Kṛṣṇa Himself is the beneﬁciary of all kinds of <em>yajñas:</em> <em>bhoktāraṁ yajña-tapasām.</em> Therefore, ultimate satisfaction of the <em>yajña-pati</em> is the chief purpose of all <em>yajñas.</em> When these <em>yajñas</em> are perfectly performed, naturally the demigods in charge of the different departments of supply are pleased, and there is no scarcity in the supply of natural products.</div>
<div class="para">Performance of <em>yajñas</em> has many side beneﬁts, ultimately leading to liberation from material bondage. By performance of <em>yajñas,</em> all activities become puriﬁed, as it is stated in the <em>Vedas:</em> <em>āhāra-śuddhau sattva-śuddhiḥ sattva-śuddhau dhruvā smṛtiḥ smṛti-lambhe sarva-granthīnāṁ vipramokṣaḥ.</em> By performance of <em>yajña</em> one’s eatables become sanctiﬁed, and by eating sanctiﬁed foodstuffs one’s very existence becomes puriﬁed; by the puriﬁcation of existence ﬁner tissues in the memory become sanctiﬁed, and when memory is sanctiﬁed one can think of the path of liberation, and all these combined together lead to Kṛṣṇa consciousness, the great necessity of present-day society.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text12" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 12</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">wí"Ana, BaAegAAna, ih" vaAe de"vaA d"Asyantae yaÁaBaAivataA: /<br />taEdR"ÔaAna‘ad"AyaEByaAe yaAe BauÈeÿ staena Wva s$a: //12//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>iṣṭān bhogān hi vo devā<br />dāsyante yajña-bhāvitāḥ<br />tair dattān apradāyaibhyo<br />yo bhuṅkte stena eva saḥ</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>iṣṭān</em>&nbsp;– desired; <em>bhogān</em>&nbsp;– necessities of life; <em>hi</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>vaḥ</em>&nbsp;– unto you; <em>devāḥ</em>&nbsp;– the demigods; <em>dāsyante</em>&nbsp;– will award; <em>yajña-bhāvitāḥ</em>&nbsp;– being satisﬁed by the performance of sacriﬁces; <em>taiḥ</em>&nbsp;– by them; <em>dattān</em>&nbsp;– things given; <em>apradāya</em>&nbsp;– without offering; <em>ebhyaḥ</em>&nbsp;– to these demigods; <em>yaḥ</em>&nbsp;– he who; <em>bhuṅkte</em>&nbsp;– enjoys; <em>stenaḥ</em>&nbsp;– thief; <em>eva</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>saḥ</em>&nbsp;– he.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>In charge of the various necessities of life, the demigods, being satisﬁed by the performance of yajña [sacriﬁce], will supply all necessities to you. But he who enjoys such gifts without offering them to the demigods in return is certainly a thief.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The demigods are authorized supplying agents on behalf of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Viṣṇu. Therefore, they must be satisﬁed by the performance of prescribed <em>yajñas.</em> In the <em>Vedas,</em> there are different kinds of <em>yajñas</em> prescribed for different kinds of demigods, but all are ultimately offered to the Supreme Personality of Godhead. For one who cannot understand what the Personality of Godhead is, sacriﬁce to the demigods is recommended. According to the different material qualities of the persons concerned, different types of <em>yajñas</em> are recommended in the <em>Vedas.</em> Worship of different demigods is also on the same basis&nbsp;– namely, according to different qualities. For example, the meat-eaters are recommended to worship the goddess Kālī, the ghastly form of material nature, and before the goddess the sacriﬁce of animals is recommended. But for those who are in the mode of goodness, the transcendental worship of Viṣṇu is recommended. But ultimately all <em>yajñas</em> are meant for gradual promotion to the transcendental position. For ordinary men, at least ﬁve <em>yajñas,</em> known as <em>pañca-mahā-yajña,</em> are necessary.</div>
<div class="para">One should know, however, that all the necessities of life that the human society requires are supplied by the demigod agents of the Lord. No one can manufacture anything. Take, for example, all the eatables of human society. These eatables include grains, fruits, vegetables, milk, sugar, etc., for the persons in the mode of goodness, and also eatables for the nonvegetarians, like meats, none of which can be manufactured by men. Then again, take for example heat, light, water, air, etc., which are also necessities of life&nbsp;– none of them can be manufactured by the human society. Without the Supreme Lord, there can be no profuse sunlight, moonlight, rainfall, breeze, etc., without which no one can live. Obviously, our life is dependent on supplies from the Lord. Even for our manufacturing enterprises, we require so many raw materials like metal, sulphur, mercury, manganese, and so many essentials&nbsp;– all of which are supplied by the agents of the Lord, with the purpose that we should make proper use of them to keep ourselves ﬁt and healthy for the purpose of self-realization, leading to the ultimate goal of life, namely, liberation from the material struggle for existence. This aim of life is attained by performance of <em>yajñas.</em> If we forget the purpose of human life and simply take supplies from the agents of the Lord for sense gratiﬁcation and become more and more entangled in material existence, which is not the purpose of creation, certainly we become thieves, and therefore we are punished by the laws of material nature. A society of thieves can never be happy, because they have no aim in life. The gross materialist thieves have no ultimate goal of life. They are simply directed to sense gratiﬁcation; nor do they have knowledge of how to perform <em>yajñas.</em> Lord Caitanya, however, inaugurated the easiest performance of <em>yajña,</em> namely the <em>saṅkīrtana-yajña,</em> which can be performed by anyone in the world who accepts the principles of Kṛṣṇa consciousness.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text13" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 13</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">yaÁaizAí"AizAna: s$antaAe maucyantae s$avaRik(ilbaSaE: /<br />BauÃatae tae tvaGaM paApaA yae pacantyaAtmak(Ar"NAAta, //13//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>yajña-śiṣṭāśinaḥ santo<br />mucyante sarva-kilbiṣaiḥ<br />bhuñjate te tv aghaṁ pāpā<br />ye pacanty ātma-kāraṇāt</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>yajña-śiṣṭa</em>&nbsp;– of food taken after performance of <em>yajña;</em> <em>aśinaḥ</em>&nbsp;– eaters; <em>santaḥ</em>&nbsp;– the devotees; <em>mucyante</em>&nbsp;– get relief; <em>sarva</em>&nbsp;– all kinds of; <em>kilbiṣaiḥ</em>&nbsp;– from sins; <em>bhuñjate</em>&nbsp;– enjoy; <em>te</em>&nbsp;– they; <em>tu</em>&nbsp;– but; <em>agham</em>&nbsp;– grievous sins; <em>pāpāḥ</em>&nbsp;– sinners; <em>ye</em>&nbsp;– who; <em>pacanti</em>&nbsp;– prepare food; <em>ātma-kāraṇāt</em>&nbsp;– for sense enjoyment.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>The devotees of the Lord are released from all kinds of sins because they eat food which is offered ﬁrst for sacriﬁce. Others, who prepare food for personal sense enjoyment, verily eat only sin.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The devotees of the Supreme Lord, or the persons who are in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, are called <em>santas,</em> and they are always in love with the Lord as it is described in the <em>Brahma-saṁhitā</em> (5.38): <em>premāñjana-cchurita-bhakti-vilocanena santaḥ sadaiva hṛdayeṣu vilokayanti.</em> The <em>santas,</em> being always in a compact of love with the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Govinda (the giver of all pleasures), or Mukunda (the giver of liberation), or Kṛṣṇa (the all-attractive person), cannot accept anything without ﬁrst offering it to the Supreme Person. Therefore, such devotees always perform <em>yajñas</em> in different modes of devotional service, such as <em>śravaṇam, kīrtanam, smaraṇam, arcanam,</em> etc., and these performances of <em>yajñas</em> keep them always aloof from all kinds of contamination of sinful association in the material world. Others, who prepare food for self or sense gratiﬁcation, are not only thieves but also the eaters of all kinds of sins. How can a person be happy if he is both a thief and sinful? It is not possible. Therefore, in order for people to become happy in all respects, they must be taught to perform the easy process of <em>saṅkīrtana-yajña,</em> in full Kṛṣṇa consciousness. Otherwise, there can be no peace or happiness in the world.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text14" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 14</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">@ªaAà"vainta BaUtaAina pajaRnyaAd"ªas$amBava: /<br />yaÁaAà"vaita pajaRnyaAe yaÁa: k(maRs$amauà"va: //14//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>annād bhavanti bhūtāni<br />parjanyād anna-sambhavaḥ<br />yajñād bhavati parjanyo<br />yajñaḥ karma-samudbhavaḥ</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>annāt</em>&nbsp;– from grains; <em>bhavanti</em>&nbsp;– grow; <em>bhūtāni</em>&nbsp;– the material bodies; <em>parjanyāt</em>&nbsp;– from rains; <em>anna</em>&nbsp;– of food grains; <em>sambhavaḥ</em>&nbsp;– production; <em>yajñāt</em>&nbsp;– from the performance of sacriﬁce; <em>bhavati</em>&nbsp;– becomes possible; <em>parjanyaḥ</em>&nbsp;– rain; <em>yajñaḥ</em>&nbsp;– performance of <em>yajña;</em> <em>karma</em>&nbsp;– prescribed duties; <em>samudbhavaḥ</em>&nbsp;– born of.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>All living bodies subsist on food grains, which are produced from rains. Rains are produced by performance of yajña [sacriﬁce], and yajña is born of prescribed duties.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">Śrīla Baladeva Vidyābhūṣaṇa, a great commentator on the <em>Bhagavad-gītā,</em> writes as follows: <em>ye indrādy-aṅgatayāvasthitaṁ yajñaṁ sarveśvaraṁ viṣṇum abhyarcya tac-cheṣam aśnanti tena tad deha-yātrāṁ sampādayanti, te santaḥ sarveśvarasya yajña-puruṣasya bhaktāḥ sarva-kilbiṣair anādi-kāla-vivṛddhair ātmānubhava-pratibandhakair nikhilaiḥ pāpair vimucyante.</em> The Supreme Lord, who is known as the <em>yajña-puruṣa,</em> or the personal beneﬁciary of all sacriﬁces, is the master of all the demigods, who serve Him as the different limbs of the body serve the whole. Demigods like Indra, Candra and Varuṇa are appointed ofﬁcers who manage material affairs, and the <em>Vedas</em> direct sacriﬁces to satisfy these demigods so that they may be pleased to supply air, light and water sufﬁciently to produce food grains. When Lord Kṛṣṇa is worshiped, the demigods, who are different limbs of the Lord, are also automatically worshiped; therefore there is no separate need to worship the demigods. For this reason, the devotees of the Lord, who are in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, offer food to Kṛṣṇa and then eat&nbsp;– a process which nourishes the body spiritually. By such action not only are past sinful reactions in the body vanquished, but the body becomes immunized to all contamination of material nature. When there is an epidemic disease, an antiseptic vaccine protects a person from the attack of such an epidemic. Similarly, food offered to Lord Viṣṇu and then taken by us makes us sufﬁciently resistant to material affection, and one who is accustomed to this practice is called a devotee of the Lord. Therefore, a person in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, who eats only food offered to Kṛṣṇa, can counteract all reactions of past material infections, which are impediments to the progress of self-realization. On the other hand, one who does not do so continues to increase the volume of sinful action, and this prepares the next body to resemble hogs and dogs, to suffer the resultant reactions of all sins. The material world is full of contaminations, and one who is immunized by accepting <em>prasādam</em> of the Lord (food offered to Viṣṇu) is saved from the attack, whereas one who does not do so becomes subjected to contamination.</div>
<div class="para">Food grains or vegetables are factually eatables. The human being eats different kinds of food grains, vegetables, fruits, etc., and the animals eat the refuse of the food grains and vegetables, grass, plants, etc. Human beings who are accustomed to eating meat and ﬂesh must also depend on the production of vegetation in order to eat the animals. Therefore, ultimately, we have to depend on the production of the ﬁeld and not on the production of big factories. The ﬁeld production is due to sufﬁcient rain from the sky, and such rains are controlled by demigods like Indra, sun, moon, etc., and they are all servants of the Lord. The Lord can be satisﬁed by sacriﬁces; therefore, one who cannot perform them will ﬁnd himself in scarcity&nbsp;– that is the law of nature. <em>Yajña,</em> speciﬁcally the <em>saṅkīrtana-yajña</em> prescribed for this age, must therefore be performed to save us at least from scarcity of food supply.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text15" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 15</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">k(maR “aöAeà"vaM ivaiÜ" “aöAºar"s$amauà"vama, /<br />tasmaAts$avaRgAtaM “aö inatyaM yaÁae ‘aitaiï"tama, //15//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>karma brahmodbhavaṁ viddhi<br />brahmākṣara-samudbhavam<br />tasmāt sarva-gataṁ brahma<br />nityaṁ yajñe pratiṣṭhitam</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>karma</em>&nbsp;– work; <em>brahma</em>&nbsp;– from the <em>Vedas;</em> <em>udbhavam</em>&nbsp;– produced; <em>viddhi</em>&nbsp;– you should know; <em>brahma</em>&nbsp;– the <em>Vedas;</em> <em>akṣara</em>&nbsp;– from the Supreme Brahman (Personality of Godhead); <em>samudbhavam</em>&nbsp;– directly manifested; <em>tasmāt</em>&nbsp;– therefore; <em>sarva-gatam</em>&nbsp;– all-pervading; <em>brahma</em>&nbsp;– transcendence; <em>nityam</em>&nbsp;– eternally; <em>yajñe</em>&nbsp;– in sacriﬁce; <em>pratiṣṭhitam</em>&nbsp;– situated.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Regulated activities are prescribed in the Vedas, and the Vedas are directly manifested from the Supreme Personality of Godhead. Consequently the all-pervading Transcendence is eternally situated in acts of sacriﬁce.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent"><em>Yajñārtha-karma, </em>or the necessity of work for the satisfaction of Kṛṣṇa only, is more expressly stated in this verse. If we have to work for the satisfaction of the <em>yajña-puruṣa,</em> Viṣṇu, then we must ﬁnd out the direction of work in Brahman, or the transcendental <em>Vedas</em>.<em> </em>The <em>Vedas </em>are therefore codes of working directions. Anything performed without the direction of the <em>Vedas</em> is called <em>vikarma, </em>or unauthorized or sinful work. Therefore, one should always take direction from the <em>Vedas</em> to be saved from the reaction of work. As one has to work in ordinary life by the direction of the state, one similarly has to work under direction of the supreme state of the Lord. Such directions in the <em>Vedas</em> are directly manifested from the breathing of the Supreme Personality of Godhead. It is said, <em>asya mahato bhūtasya niśvasitam etad yad ṛg-vedo yajur-vedaḥ sāma-vedo ’tharvāṅgirasaḥ.</em> “The four <em>Vedas&nbsp;– </em>namely the <em>Ṛg Veda, Yajur Veda, Sāma Veda </em>and <em>Atharva Veda</em>&nbsp;– are all emanations from the breathing of the great Personality of Godhead.” (<em>Bṛhad-āraṇyaka Upaniṣad</em> 4.5.11) The Lord, being omnipotent, can speak by breathing air, for as it is conﬁrmed in the <em>Brahma-saṁhitā,</em> the Lord has the omnipotence to perform through each of His senses the actions of all other senses. In other words, the Lord can speak through His breathing, and He can impregnate by His eyes. In fact, it is said that He glanced over material nature and thus fathered all living entities. After creating or impregnating the conditioned souls into the womb of material nature, He gave His directions in the Vedic wisdom as to how such conditioned souls can return home, back to Godhead. We should always remember that the conditioned souls in material nature are all eager for material enjoyment. But the Vedic directions are so made that one can satisfy one’s perverted desires, then return to Godhead, having ﬁnished his so-called enjoyment. It is a chance for the conditioned souls to attain liberation; therefore the conditioned souls must try to follow the process of <em>yajña</em> by becoming Kṛṣṇa conscious. Even those who have not followed the Vedic injunctions may adopt the principles of Kṛṣṇa consciousness, and that will take the place of performance of Vedic <em>yajñas,</em> or <em>karmas</em>.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text16" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 16</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">WvaM ‘avaitaRtaM ca‚M( naAnauvataRyataIh" ya: /<br />@GaAyauir"in‰"yaAr"AmaAe maAeGaM paATaR s$a jaIvaita //16//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>evaṁ pravartitaṁ cakraṁ<br />nānuvartayatīha yaḥ<br />aghāyur indriyārāmo<br />moghaṁ pārtha sa jīvati</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>evam</em>&nbsp;– thus; <em>pravartitam</em>&nbsp;– established by the <em>Vedas;</em> <em>cakram</em>&nbsp;– cycle; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– does not; <em>anuvartayati</em>&nbsp;– adopt; <em>iha</em>&nbsp;– in this life; <em>yaḥ</em>&nbsp;– one who; <em>agha-āyuḥ</em>&nbsp;– whose life is full of sins; <em>indriya-ārāmaḥ</em>&nbsp;– satisﬁed in sense gratiﬁcation; <em>mogham</em>&nbsp;– uselessly; <em>pārtha</em>&nbsp;– O son of Pṛthā (Arjuna); <em>saḥ</em>&nbsp;– he; <em>jīvati</em>&nbsp;– lives.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>My dear Arjuna, one who does not follow in human life the cycle of sacriﬁce thus established by the Vedas certainly leads a life full of sin. Living only for the satisfaction of the senses, such a person lives in vain.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The mammonist philosophy of “work very hard and enjoy sense gratiﬁcation” is condemned herein by the Lord. Therefore, for those who want to enjoy this material world, the above-mentioned cycle of performing <em>yajñas</em> is absolutely necessary. One who does not follow such regulations is living a very risky life, being condemned more and more. By nature’s law, this human form of life is speciﬁcally meant for self-realization, in either of the three ways&nbsp;– namely <em>karma-yoga, jñāna-yoga</em> or <em>bhakti-yoga.</em> There is no necessity of rigidly following the performances of the prescribed <em>yajñas</em> for the transcendentalists who are above vice and virtue; but those who are engaged in sense gratiﬁcation require puriﬁcation by the above-mentioned cycle of <em>yajña</em> performances. There are different kinds of activities. Those who are not Kṛṣṇa conscious are certainly engaged in sensory consciousness; therefore they need to execute pious work. The <em>yajña</em> system is planned in such a way that sensory conscious persons may satisfy their desires without becoming entangled in the reaction of sense-gratiﬁcatory work. The prosperity of the world depends not on our own efforts but on the background arrangement of the Supreme Lord, directly carried out by the demigods. Therefore, the <em>yajñas</em> are directly aimed at the particular demigods mentioned in the <em>Vedas.</em> Indirectly, it is the practice of Kṛṣṇa consciousness, because when one masters the performance of <em>yajñas</em> one is sure to become Kṛṣṇa conscious. But if by performing <em>yajñas</em> one does not become Kṛṣṇa conscious, such principles are counted as only moral codes. One should not, therefore, limit his progress only to the point of moral codes, but should transcend them, to attain Kṛṣṇa consciousness.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text17" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 17</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">yastvaAtmar"itare"va syaAd"Atmata{æaê maAnava: /<br />@Atmanyaeva ca s$antauí"stasya k(Aya&lt; na ivaâtae //17//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>yas tv ātma-ratir eva syād<br />ātma-tṛptaś ca mānavaḥ<br />ātmany eva ca santuṣṭas<br />tasya kāryaṁ na vidyate</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>yaḥ</em>&nbsp;– one who; <em>tu</em>&nbsp;– but; <em>ātma-ratiḥ</em>&nbsp;– taking pleasure in the Self; <em>eva</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>syāt</em>&nbsp;– remains; <em>ātma-tṛptaḥ</em>&nbsp;– self-illuminated; <em>ca</em>&nbsp;– and; <em>mānavaḥ</em>&nbsp;– a man; <em>ātmani</em>&nbsp;– in himself; <em>eva</em>&nbsp;– only; <em>ca</em>&nbsp;– and; <em>santuṣṭaḥ</em>&nbsp;– perfectly satiated; <em>tasya</em>&nbsp;– his; <em>kāryam</em>&nbsp;– duty; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– does not; <em>vidyate</em>&nbsp;– exist.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>But for one who takes pleasure in the Self, whose human life is one of self-realization, and who is satisﬁed in the Self only, fully satiated&nbsp;– for him there is no duty.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">A person who is <em>fully</em> Kṛṣṇa conscious, and is fully satisﬁed by his acts in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, no longer has any duty to perform. Due to his being Kṛṣṇa conscious, all impiety within is instantly cleansed, an effect of many, many thousands of <em>yajña</em> performances. By such clearing of consciousness, one becomes fully conﬁdent of his eternal position in relationship with the Supreme. His duty thus becomes self-illuminated by the grace of the Lord, and therefore he no longer has any obligations to the Vedic injunctions. Such a Kṛṣṇa conscious person is no longer interested in material activities and no longer takes pleasure in material arrangements like wine, women and similar infatuations.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text18" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 18</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">naEva tasya k{(taenaATaAeR naAk{(taenaeh" k(êna /<br />na caAsya s$avaRBaUtaeSau k(iêd"TaRvyapaA™aya: //18//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>naiva tasya kṛtenārtho<br />nākṛteneha kaścana<br />na cāsya sarva-bhūteṣu<br />kaścid artha-vyapāśrayaḥ</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>na</em>&nbsp;– never; <em>eva</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>tasya</em>&nbsp;– his; <em>kṛtena</em>&nbsp;– by discharge of duty; <em>arthaḥ</em>&nbsp;– purpose; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– nor; <em>akṛtena</em>&nbsp;– without discharge of duty; <em>iha</em>&nbsp;– in this world; <em>kaścana</em>&nbsp;– whatever; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– never; <em>ca</em>&nbsp;– and; <em>asya</em>&nbsp;– of him; <em>sarva-bhūteṣu</em>&nbsp;– among all living beings; <em>kaścit</em>&nbsp;– any; <em>artha</em>&nbsp;– purpose; <em>vyapāśrayaḥ</em>&nbsp;– taking shelter of.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>A self-realized man has no purpose to fulﬁll in the discharge of his prescribed duties, nor has he any reason not to perform such work. Nor has he any need to depend on any other living being.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">A self-realized man is no longer obliged to perform any prescribed duty, save and except activities in Kṛṣṇa consciousness. Kṛṣṇa consciousness is not inactivity either, as will be explained in the following verses. A Kṛṣṇa conscious man does not take shelter of any person&nbsp;– man or demigod. Whatever he does in Kṛṣṇa consciousness is sufﬁcient in the discharge of his obligation.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text19" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 19</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">tasmaAd"s$a·(: s$atataM k(Aya&lt; k(maR s$amaAcar" /<br />@s$a·(Ae ÷Acar"na, k(maR par"maA«aAeita paUç&amp;Sa: //19//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>tasmād asaktaḥ satataṁ<br />kāryaṁ karma samācara<br />asakto hy ācaran karma<br />param āpnoti pūruṣaḥ</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>tasmāt</em>&nbsp;– therefore; <em>asaktaḥ</em>&nbsp;– without attachment; <em>satatam</em>&nbsp;– constantly; <em>kāryam</em>&nbsp;– as duty; <em>karma</em>&nbsp;– work; <em>samācara</em>&nbsp;– perform; <em>asaktaḥ</em>&nbsp;– unattached; <em>hi</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>ācaran</em>&nbsp;– performing; <em>karma</em>&nbsp;– work; <em>param</em>&nbsp;– the Supreme; <em>āpnoti</em>&nbsp;– achieves; <em>pūruṣaḥ</em>&nbsp;– a man.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Therefore, without being attached to the fruits of activities, one should act as a matter of duty, for by working without attachment one attains the Supreme.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The Supreme is the Personality of Godhead for the devotees, and liberation for the impersonalist. A person, therefore, acting for Kṛṣṇa, or in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, under proper guidance and without attachment to the result of the work, is certainly making progress toward the supreme goal of life. Arjuna is told that he should ﬁght in the Battle of Kurukṣetra for the interest of Kṛṣṇa because Kṛṣṇa wanted him to ﬁght. To be a good man or a nonviolent man is a personal attachment, but to act on behalf of the Supreme is to act without attachment for the result. That is perfect action of the highest degree, recommended by the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Śrī Kṛṣṇa.</div>
<div class="para">Vedic rituals, like prescribed sacriﬁces, are performed for puriﬁcation of impious activities that were performed in the ﬁeld of sense gratiﬁcation. But action in Kṛṣṇa consciousness is transcendental to the reactions of good or evil work. A Kṛṣṇa conscious person has no attachment for the result but acts on behalf of Kṛṣṇa alone. He engages in all kinds of activities, but is completely nonattached.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text20" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 20</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">k(maRNAEva ih" s$aMis$aiÜ"maAisTataA janak(Ad"ya: /<br />laAek(s$aÍÿh"maevaAipa s$ampazyana, k(tauRmahR"is$a //20//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>karmaṇaiva hi saṁsiddhim<br />āsthitā janakādayaḥ<br />loka-saṅgraham evāpi<br />sampaśyan kartum arhasi</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>karmaṇā</em>&nbsp;– by work; <em>eva</em>&nbsp;– even; <em>hi</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>saṁsiddhim</em>&nbsp;– in perfection; <em>āsthitāḥ</em>&nbsp;– situated; <em>janaka-ādayaḥ</em>&nbsp;– Janaka and other kings; <em>loka-saṅgraham</em>&nbsp;– the people in general; <em>eva api</em>&nbsp;– also; <em>sampaśyan</em>&nbsp;– considering; <em>kartum</em>&nbsp;– to act; <em>arhasi</em>&nbsp;– you deserve.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Kings such as Janaka attained perfection solely by performance of prescribed duties. Therefore, just for the sake of educating the people in general, you should perform your work.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">Kings like Janaka were all self-realized souls; consequently they had no obligation to perform the prescribed duties in the <em>Vedas.</em> Nonetheless they performed all prescribed activities just to set examples for the people in general. Janaka was the father of Sītā and father-in-law of Lord Śrī Rāma. Being a great devotee of the Lord, he was transcendentally situated, but because he was the king of Mithilā (a subdivision of Bihar province in India), he had to teach his subjects how to perform prescribed duties. Lord Kṛṣṇa and Arjuna, the Lord’s eternal friend, had no need to ﬁght in the Battle of Kurukṣetra, but they fought to teach people in general that violence is also necessary in a situation where good arguments fail. Before the Battle of Kurukṣetra, every effort was made to avoid the war, even by the Supreme Personality of Godhead, but the other party was determined to ﬁght. So for such a right cause, there is a necessity for ﬁghting. Although one who is situated in Kṛṣṇa consciousness may not have any interest in the world, he still works to teach the public how to live and how to act. Experienced persons in Kṛṣṇa consciousness can act in such a way that others will follow, and this is explained in the following verse.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text21" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 21</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">yaâd"Acar"ita ™aeï"staÔade"vaetar"Ae jana: /<br />s$a yat‘amaANAM ku(ç&amp;tae laAek(stad"nauvataRtae //21//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>yad yad ācarati śreṣṭhas<br />tat tad evetaro janaḥ<br />sa yat pramāṇaṁ kurute<br />lokas tad anuvartate</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>yat yat</em>&nbsp;– whatever; <em>ācarati</em>&nbsp;– he does; <em>śreṣṭhaḥ</em>&nbsp;– a respectable leader; <em>tat</em>&nbsp;– that; <em>tat</em>&nbsp;– and that alone; <em>eva</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>itaraḥ</em>&nbsp;– common; <em>janaḥ</em>&nbsp;– person; <em>saḥ</em>&nbsp;– he; <em>yat</em>&nbsp;– whichever; <em>pramāṇam</em>&nbsp;– example; <em>kurute</em>&nbsp;– does perform; <em>lokaḥ</em>&nbsp;– all the world; <em>tat</em>&nbsp;– that; <em>anuvartate</em>&nbsp;– follows in the footsteps.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Whatever action a great man performs, common men follow. And whatever standards he sets by exemplary acts, all the world pursues.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">People in general always require a leader who can teach the public by practical behavior. A leader cannot teach the public to stop smoking if he himself smokes. Lord Caitanya said that a teacher should behave properly before he begins teaching. One who teaches in that way is called <em>ācārya,</em> or the ideal teacher. Therefore, a teacher must follow the principles of <em>śāstra</em> (scripture) to teach the common man. The teacher cannot manufacture rules against the principles of revealed scriptures. The revealed scriptures, like <em>Manu-saṁhitā</em> and similar others, are considered the standard books to be followed by human society. Thus the leader’s teaching should be based on the principles of such standard <em>śāstras.</em> One who desires to improve himself must follow the standard rules as they are practiced by the great teachers. The <em>Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam</em> also afﬁrms that one should follow in the footsteps of great devotees, and that is the way of progress on the path of spiritual realization. The king or the executive head of a state, the father and the schoolteacher are all considered to be natural leaders of the innocent people in general. All such natural leaders have a great responsibility to their dependents; therefore they must be conversant with standard books of moral and spiritual codes.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text22" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 22</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">na mae paATaARista k(taRvyaM i‡aSau laAeke(Sau ik(Âana /<br />naAnavaAæamavaAæavyaM vataR Wva ca k(maRiNA //22//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>na me pārthāsti kartavyaṁ<br />triṣu lokeṣu kiñcana<br />nānavāptam avāptavyaṁ<br />varta eva ca karmaṇi</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>na</em>&nbsp;– not; <em>me</em>&nbsp;– Mine; <em>pārtha</em>&nbsp;– O son of Pṛthā; <em>asti</em>&nbsp;– there is; <em>kartavyam</em>&nbsp;– prescribed duty; <em>triṣu</em>&nbsp;– in the three; <em>lokeṣu</em>&nbsp;– planetary systems; <em>kiñcana</em>&nbsp;– any; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– nothing; <em>anavāptam</em>&nbsp;– wanted; <em>avāptavyam</em>&nbsp;– to be gained; <em>varte</em>&nbsp;– I am engaged; <em>eva</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>ca</em>&nbsp;– also; <em>karmaṇi</em>&nbsp;– in prescribed duty.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>O son of Pṛthā, there is no work prescribed for Me within all the three planetary systems. Nor am I in want of anything, nor have I a need to obtain anything&nbsp;– and yet I am engaged in prescribed duties.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The Supreme Personality of Godhead is described in the Vedic literatures as follows:</div>
<div class="verse-in-purp"><em>tam īśvarāṇāṁ paramaṁ maheśvaraṁ<br />taṁ devatānāṁ paramaṁ ca daivatam<br />patiṁ patīnāṁ paramaṁ parastād<br />vidāma devaṁ bhuvaneśam īḍyam</em></div>
<div class="verse-in-purp"><em>na tasya kāryaṁ karaṇaṁ ca vidyate<br />na tat-samaś cābhyadhikaś ca dṛśyate<br />parāsya śaktir vividhaiva śrūyate<br />svābhāvikī jñāna-bala-kriyā ca</em></div>
<div class="purp">“The Supreme Lord is the controller of all other controllers, and He is the greatest of all the diverse planetary leaders. Everyone is under His control. All entities are delegated with particular power only by the Supreme Lord; they are not supreme themselves. He is also worshipable by all demigods and is the supreme director of all directors. Therefore, He is transcendental to all kinds of material leaders and controllers and is worshipable by all. There is no one greater than Him, and He is the supreme cause of all causes.</div>
<div class="para">“He does not possess a bodily form like that of an ordinary living entity. There is no difference between His body and His soul. He is absolute. All His senses are transcendental. Any one of His senses can perform the action of any other sense. Therefore, no one is greater than Him or equal to Him. His potencies are multifarious, and thus His deeds are automatically performed as a natural sequence.”<strong> </strong>(<em>Śvetāśvatara Upaniṣad </em>6.7–8)</div>
<div class="para">Since everything is in full opulence in the Personality of Godhead and is existing in full truth, there is no duty for the Supreme Personality of Godhead to perform. One who must receive the results of work has some designated duty, but one who has nothing to achieve within the three planetary systems certainly has no duty. And yet Lord Kṛṣṇa is engaged on the Battleﬁeld of Kurukṣetra as the leader of the <em>kṣatriyas</em> because the <em>kṣatriyas</em> are duty-bound to give protection to the distressed. Although He is above all the regulations of the revealed scriptures, He does not do anything that violates the revealed scriptures.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text23" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 23</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">yaid" ÷hM" na vataeRyaM jaAtau k(maRNyatain‰"ta: /<br />mama vatmaARnauvataRntae manauSyaA: paATaR s$avaRzA: //23//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>yadi hy ahaṁ na varteyaṁ<br />jātu karmaṇy atandritaḥ<br />mama vartmānuvartante<br />manuṣyāḥ pārtha sarvaśaḥ</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>yadi</em>&nbsp;– if; <em>hi</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>aham</em>&nbsp;– I; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– do not; <em>varteyam</em>&nbsp;– thus engage; <em>jātu</em>&nbsp;– ever; <em>karmaṇi</em>&nbsp;– in the performance of prescribed duties; <em>atandritaḥ</em>&nbsp;– with great care; <em>mama</em>&nbsp;– My; <em>vartma</em>&nbsp;– path; <em>anuvartante</em>&nbsp;– would follow; <em>manuṣyāḥ</em>&nbsp;– all men; <em>pārtha</em>&nbsp;– O son of Pṛthā; <em>sarvaśaḥ</em>&nbsp;– in all respects.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>For if I ever failed to engage in carefully performing prescribed duties, O Pārtha, certainly all men would follow My path.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">In order to keep the balance of social tranquillity for progress in spiritual life, there are traditional family usages meant for every civilized man. Although such rules and regulations are for the conditioned souls and not Lord Kṛṣṇa, because He descended to establish the principles of religion He followed the prescribed rules. Otherwise, common men would follow in His footsteps, because He is the greatest authority. From the <em>Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam</em> it is understood that Lord Kṛṣṇa was performing all the religious duties at home and out of home, as required of a householder.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text24" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 24</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">ots$aIde"yauir"mae laAek(A na ku(yaA&lt; k(maR caed"h"ma, /<br />s$aÆÿr"sya ca k(taAR syaAmaupah"nyaAimamaA: ‘ajaA: //24//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>utsīdeyur ime lokā<br />na kuryāṁ karma ced aham<br />saṅkarasya ca kartā syām<br />upahanyām imāḥ prajāḥ</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>utsīdeyuḥ</em>&nbsp;– would be put into ruin; <em>ime</em>&nbsp;– all these; <em>lokāḥ</em>&nbsp;– worlds; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– not; <em>kuryām</em>&nbsp;– I perform; <em>karma</em>&nbsp;– prescribed duties; <em>cet</em>&nbsp;– if; <em>aham</em>&nbsp;– I; <em>saṅkarasya</em>&nbsp;– of unwanted population; <em>ca</em>&nbsp;– and; <em>kartā</em>&nbsp;– creator; <em>syām</em>&nbsp;– would be; <em>upahanyām</em>&nbsp;– would destroy; <em>imāḥ</em>&nbsp;– all these; <em>prajāḥ</em>&nbsp;– living entities.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>If I did not perform prescribed duties, all these worlds would be put to ruination. I would be the cause of creating unwanted population, and I would thereby destroy the peace of all living beings.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent"><em>Varṇa-saṅkara</em> is unwanted population which disturbs the peace of the general society. In order to check this social disturbance, there are prescribed rules and regulations by which the population can automatically become peaceful and organized for spiritual progress in life. When Lord Kṛṣṇa descends, naturally He deals with such rules and regulations in order to maintain the prestige and necessity of such important performances. The Lord is the father of all living entities, and if the living entities are misguided, indirectly the responsibility goes to the Lord. Therefore, whenever there is general disregard of regulative principles, the Lord Himself descends and corrects the society. We should, however, note carefully that although we have to follow in the footsteps of the Lord, we still have to remember that we cannot imitate Him. Following and imitating are not on the same level. We cannot imitate the Lord by lifting Govardhana Hill, as the Lord did in His childhood. It is impossible for any human being. We have to follow His instructions, but we may not imitate Him at any time. The <em>Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam</em> (10.33.30–31) afﬁrms:</div>
<div class="verse-in-purp"><em>naitat samācarej jātu<br />manasāpi hy anīśvaraḥ<br />vinaśyaty ācaran mauḍhyād<br />yathārudro ’bdhi-jaṁ viṣam</em></div>
<div class="verse-in-purp"><em>īśvarāṇāṁ vacaḥ satyaṁ<br />tathaivācaritaṁ kvacit<br />teṣāṁ yat sva-vaco-yuktaṁ<br />buddhimāṁs tat samācaret</em></div>
<div class="purp">“One should simply follow the instructions of the Lord and His empowered servants. Their instructions are all good for us, and any intelligent person will perform them as instructed. However, one should guard against trying to imitate their actions. One should not try to drink the ocean of poison in imitation of Lord Śiva.”</div>
<div class="para">We should always consider the position of the <em>īśvaras,</em> or those who can actually control the movements of the sun and moon, as superior. Without such power, one cannot imitate the <em>īśvaras,</em> who are superpowerful. Lord Śiva drank poison to the extent of swallowing an ocean, but if any common man tries to drink even a fragment of such poison, he will be killed. There are many pseudo devotees of Lord Śiva who want to indulge in smoking <em>gañjā</em> (marijuana) and similar intoxicating drugs, forgetting that by so imitating the acts of Lord Śiva they are calling death very near. Similarly, there are some pseudo devotees of Lord Kṛṣṇa who prefer to imitate the Lord in His <em>rāsa-līlā,</em> or dance of love, forgetting their inability to lift Govardhana Hill. It is best, therefore, that one not try to imitate the powerful, but simply follow their instructions; nor should one try to occupy their posts without qualiﬁcation. There are so many “incarnations” of God without the power of the Supreme Godhead.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text25" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 25</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">s$a·(A: k(maRNyaivaã"AMs$aAe yaTaA ku(vaRinta BaAr"ta /<br />ku(yaARiã"ã"AMstaTaAs$a·(iêk(LSauRlaAeRk(s$aÍÿh"ma, //25//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>saktāḥ karmaṇy avidvāṁso<br />yathā kurvanti bhārata<br />kuryād vidvāṁs tathāsaktaś<br />cikīrṣur loka-saṅgraham</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>saktāḥ</em>&nbsp;– being attached; <em>karmaṇi</em>&nbsp;– in prescribed duties; <em>avidvāṁsaḥ</em>&nbsp;– the ignorant; <em>yathā</em>&nbsp;– as much as; <em>kurvanti</em>&nbsp;– they do; <em>bhārata</em>&nbsp;– O descendant of Bharata; <em>kuryāt</em>&nbsp;– must do; <em>vidvān</em>&nbsp;– the learned; <em>tathā</em>&nbsp;– thus; <em>asaktaḥ</em>&nbsp;– without attachment; <em>cikīrṣuḥ</em>&nbsp;– desiring to lead; <em>loka-saṅgraham</em>&nbsp;– the people in general.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>As the ignorant perform their duties with attachment to results, the learned may similarly act, but without attachment, for the sake of leading people on the right path.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">A person in Kṛṣṇa consciousness and a person not in Kṛṣṇa consciousness are differentiated by different desires. A Kṛṣṇa conscious person does not do anything which is not conducive to development of Kṛṣṇa consciousness. He may even act exactly like the ignorant person, who is too much attached to material activities, but one is engaged in such activities for the satisfaction of his sense gratiﬁcation, whereas the other is engaged for the satisfaction of Kṛṣṇa. Therefore, the Kṛṣṇa conscious person is required to show the people how to act and how to engage the results of action for the purpose of Kṛṣṇa consciousness.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text26" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 26</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">na bauiÜ"BaedM" janayaed"ÁaAnaAM k(maRs$aiËÿnaAma, /<br />jaAeSayaets$avaRk(maARiNA ivaã"Ana, yau·(: s$amaAcar"na, //26//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>na buddhi-bhedaṁ janayed<br />ajñānāṁ karma-saṅginām<br />joṣayet sarva-karmāṇi<br />vidvān yuktaḥ samācaran</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>na</em>&nbsp;– not; <em>buddhi-bhedam</em>&nbsp;– disruption of intelligence; <em>janayet</em>&nbsp;– he should cause; <em>ajñānām</em>&nbsp;– of the foolish; <em>karma-saṅginām</em>&nbsp;– who are attached to fruitive work; <em>joṣayet</em>&nbsp;– he should dovetail; <em>sarva</em>&nbsp;– all; <em>karmāṇi</em>&nbsp;– work; <em>vidvān</em>&nbsp;– a learned person; <em>yuktaḥ</em>&nbsp;– engaged; <em>samācaran</em>&nbsp;– practicing.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>So as not to disrupt the minds of ignorant men attached to the fruitive results of prescribed duties, a learned person should not induce them to stop work. Rather, by working in the spirit of devotion, he should engage them in all sorts of activities [for the gradual development of Kṛṣṇa consciousness].</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent"><em>Vedaiś ca sarvair aham eva vedyaḥ</em>.<em> </em>That is the end of all Vedic rituals. All rituals, all performances of sacriﬁces, and everything that is put into the <em>Vedas,</em> including all direction for material activities, are meant for understanding Kṛṣṇa, who is the ultimate goal of life. But because the conditioned souls do not know anything beyond sense gratiﬁcation, they study the <em>Vedas </em>to that end. But through fruitive activities and sense gratiﬁcation regulated by the Vedic rituals one is gradually elevated to Kṛṣṇa consciousness. Therefore a realized soul in Kṛṣṇa consciousness should not disturb others in their activities or understanding, but he should act by showing how the results of all work can be dedicated to the service of Kṛṣṇa. The learned Kṛṣṇa conscious person may act in such a way that the ignorant person working for sense gratiﬁcation may learn how to act and how to behave. Although the ignorant man is not to be disturbed in his activities, a slightly developed Kṛṣṇa conscious person may directly be engaged in the service of the Lord without waiting for other Vedic formulas. For this fortunate man there is no need to follow the Vedic rituals, because by direct Kṛṣṇa consciousness one can have all the results one would otherwise derive from following one’s prescribed duties.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text27" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 27</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">‘ak{(tae: i‚(yamaANAAina gAuNAE: k(maARiNA s$avaRzA: /<br />@h"ÆÿAr"ivamaUX#AtmaA k(taARh"imaita manyatae //27//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>prakṛteḥ kriyamāṇāni<br />guṇaiḥ karmāṇi sarvaśaḥ<br />ahaṅkāra-vimūḍhātmā<br />kartāham iti manyate</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>prakṛteḥ</em>&nbsp;– of material nature; <em>kriyamāṇāni</em>&nbsp;– being done; <em>guṇaiḥ</em>&nbsp;– by the modes; <em>karmāṇi</em>&nbsp;– activities; <em>sarvaśaḥ</em>&nbsp;– all kinds of; <em>ahaṅkāra-vimūḍha</em>&nbsp;– bewildered by false ego; <em>ātmā</em>&nbsp;– the spirit soul; <em>kartā</em>&nbsp;– doer; <em>aham</em>&nbsp;– I; <em>iti</em>&nbsp;– thus; <em>manyate</em>&nbsp;– he thinks.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>The spirit soul bewildered by the inﬂuence of false ego thinks himself the doer of activities that are in actuality carried out by the three modes of material nature.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">Two persons, one in Kṛṣṇa consciousness and the other in material consciousness, working on the same level, may appear to be working on the same platform, but there is a wide gulf of difference in their respective positions. The person in material consciousness is convinced by false ego that he is the doer of everything. He does not know that the mechanism of the body is produced by material nature, which works under the supervision of the Supreme Lord. The materialistic person has no knowledge that ultimately he is under the control of Kṛṣṇa. The person in false ego takes all credit for doing everything independently, and that is the symptom of his nescience. He does not know that this gross and subtle body is the creation of material nature, under the order of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, and as such his bodily and mental activities should be engaged in the service of Kṛṣṇa, in Kṛṣṇa consciousness. The ignorant man forgets that the Supreme Personality of Godhead is known as Hṛṣīkeśa, or the master of the senses of the material body, for due to his long misuse of the senses in sense gratiﬁcation, he is factually bewildered by the false ego, which makes him forget his eternal relationship with Kṛṣṇa.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text28" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 28</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">taÔvaivaÔau mah"AbaAh"Ae gAuNAk(maRivaBaAgAyaAe: /<br />gAuNAA gAuNAeSau vataRnta wita matvaA na s$aÀatae //28//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>tattva-vit tu mahā-bāho<br />guṇa-karma-vibhāgayoḥ<br />guṇā guṇeṣu vartanta<br />iti matvā na sajjate</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>tattva-vit</em>&nbsp;– the knower of the Absolute Truth; <em>tu</em>&nbsp;– but; <em>mahā-bāho</em>&nbsp;– O mighty-armed one; <em>guṇa-karma</em>&nbsp;– of works under material inﬂuence; <em>vibhāgayoḥ</em>&nbsp;– differences; <em>guṇāḥ</em>&nbsp;– senses; <em>guṇeṣu</em>&nbsp;– in sense gratiﬁcation; <em>vartante</em>&nbsp;– are being engaged; <em>iti</em>&nbsp;– thus; <em>matvā</em>&nbsp;– thinking; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– never; <em>sajjate</em>&nbsp;– becomes attached.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>One who is in knowledge of the Absolute Truth, O mighty-armed, does not engage himself in the senses and sense gratiﬁcation, knowing well the differences between work in devotion and work for fruitive results.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The knower of the Absolute Truth is convinced of his awkward position in material association. He knows that he is part and parcel of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Kṛṣṇa, and that his position should not be in the material creation. He knows his real identity as part and parcel of the Supreme, who is eternal bliss and knowledge, and he realizes that somehow or other he is entrapped in the material conception of life. In his pure state of existence he is meant to dovetail his activities in devotional service to the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Kṛṣṇa. He therefore engages himself in the activities of Kṛṣṇa consciousness and becomes naturally unattached to the activities of the material senses, which are all circumstantial and temporary. He knows that his material condition of life is under the supreme control of the Lord; consequently he is not disturbed by all kinds of material reactions, which he considers to be the mercy of the Lord. According to <em>Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam,</em> one who knows the Absolute Truth in three different features&nbsp;– namely Brahman, Paramātmā and the Supreme Personality of Godhead&nbsp;– is called <em>tattva-vit,</em> for he knows also his own factual position in relationship with the Supreme.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text29" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 29</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">‘ak{(taegAuRNAs$ammaUX#A: s$aÀantae gAuNAk(maRs$au /<br />taAnak{(tµaivad"Ae mand"Ana, k{(tµaivaªa ivacaAlayaeta, //29//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>prakṛter guṇa-sammūḍhāḥ<br />sajjante guṇa-karmasu<br />tān akṛtsna-vido mandān<br />kṛtsna-vin na vicālayet</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>prakṛteḥ</em>&nbsp;– of material nature; <em>guṇa</em>&nbsp;– by the modes; <em>sammūḍhāḥ</em>&nbsp;– befooled by material identiﬁcation; <em>sajjante</em>&nbsp;– they become engaged; <em>guṇa-karmasu</em>&nbsp;– in material activities; <em>tān</em>&nbsp;– those; <em>akṛtsna-vidaḥ</em>&nbsp;– persons with a poor fund of knowledge; <em>mandān</em>&nbsp;– lazy to understand self-realization; <em>kṛtsna-vit</em>&nbsp;– one who is in factual knowledge; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– not; <em>vicālayet</em>&nbsp;– should try to agitate.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Bewildered by the modes of material nature, the ignorant fully engage themselves in material activities and become attached. But the wise should not unsettle them, although these duties are inferior due to the performers’ lack of knowledge.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">Persons who are unknowledgeable falsely identify with gross material consciousness and are full of material designations. This body is a gift of the material nature, and one who is too much attached to the bodily consciousness is called <em>manda,</em> or a lazy person without understanding of spirit soul. Ignorant men think of the body as the self; they accept bodily connections with others as kinsmanship, the land in which the body is obtained is their object of worship, and they consider the formalities of religious rituals to be ends in themselves. Social work, nationalism and altruism are some of the activities for such materially designated persons. Under the spell of such designations, they are always busy in the material ﬁeld; for them spiritual realization is a myth, and so they are not interested. Those who are enlightened in spiritual life, however, should not try to agitate such materially engrossed persons. Better to prosecute one’s own spiritual activities silently. Such bewildered persons may be engaged in such primary moral principles of life as nonviolence and similar materially benevolent work.</div>
<div class="para">Men who are ignorant cannot appreciate activities in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, and therefore Lord Kṛṣṇa advises us not to disturb them and simply waste valuable time. But the devotees of the Lord are more kind than the Lord because they understand the purpose of the Lord. Consequently they undertake all kinds of risks, even to the point of approaching ignorant men to try to engage them in the acts of Kṛṣṇa consciousness, which are absolutely necessary for the human being.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text30" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 30</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">maiya s$avaARiNA k(maARiNA s$aªyasyaADyaAtmacaetas$aA /<br />inar"AzAIinaRmaRmaAe BaUtvaA yauDyasva ivagAtajvar": //30//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans">mayi sarvāṇi karmāṇi<br />sannyasyādhyātma-cetasā<br />nirāśīr nirmamo bhūtvā<br />yudhyasva vigata-jvaraḥ</div>
<div class="wbw"><em>mayi</em>&nbsp;– unto Me; <em>sarvāṇi</em>&nbsp;– all sorts of; <em>karmāṇi</em>&nbsp;– activities; <em>sannyasya</em>&nbsp;– giving up completely; <em>adhyātma</em>&nbsp;– with full knowledge of the self; <em>cetasā</em>&nbsp;– by consciousness; <em>nirāśīḥ</em>&nbsp;– without desire for proﬁt; <em>nirmamaḥ</em>&nbsp;– without ownership; <em>bhūtvā</em>&nbsp;– so being; <em>yudhyasva</em>&nbsp;– ﬁght; <em>vigata-jvaraḥ</em>&nbsp;– without being lethargic.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Therefore, O Arjuna, surrendering all your works unto Me, with full knowledge of Me, without desires for proﬁt, with no claims to proprietorship, and free from lethargy, ﬁght.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">This verse clearly indicates the purpose of the <em>Bhagavad-gītā.</em> The Lord instructs that one has to become fully Kṛṣṇa conscious to discharge duties, as if in military discipline. Such an injunction may make things a little difﬁcult; nevertheless duties must be carried out, with dependence on Kṛṣṇa, because that is the constitutional position of the living entity. The living entity cannot be happy independent of the cooperation of the Supreme Lord, because the eternal constitutional position of the living entity is to become subordinate to the desires of the Lord. Arjuna was therefore ordered by Śrī Kṛṣṇa to ﬁght as if the Lord were his military commander. One has to sacriﬁce everything for the good will of the Supreme Lord, and at the same time discharge prescribed duties without claiming proprietorship. Arjuna did not have to consider the order of the Lord; he had only to execute His order. The Supreme Lord is the soul of all souls; therefore, one who depends solely and wholly on the Supreme Soul without personal consideration, or in other words, one who is fully Kṛṣṇa conscious, is called <em>adhyātma-cetās.</em> <em>Nirāśīḥ</em> means that one has to act on the order of the master but should not expect fruitive results. The cashier may count millions of dollars for his employer, but he does not claim a cent for himself. Similarly, one has to realize that nothing in the world belongs to any individual person, but that everything belongs to the Supreme Lord. That is the real purport of <em>mayi,</em> or “unto Me.” And when one acts in such Kṛṣṇa consciousness, certainly he does not claim proprietorship over anything. This consciousness is called <em>nirmama,</em> or “nothing is mine.” And if there is any reluctance to execute such a stern order, which is without consideration of so-called kinsmen in the bodily relationship, that reluctance should be thrown off; in this way one may become <em>vigata-jvara,</em> or without feverish mentality or lethargy. Everyone, according to his quality and position, has a particular type of work to discharge, and all such duties may be discharged in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, as described above. That will lead one to the path of liberation.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text31" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 31</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">yae mae mataimadM" inatyamanauitaï"inta maAnavaA: /<br />™aÜ"AvantaAe'nas$aUyantaAe maucyantae tae'ipa k(maRiBa: //31//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>ye me matam idaṁ nityam<br />anutiṣṭhanti mānavāḥ<br />śraddhāvanto ’nasūyanto<br />mucyante te ’pi karmabhiḥ</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>ye</em>&nbsp;– those who; <em>me</em>&nbsp;– My; <em>matam</em>&nbsp;– injunctions; <em>idam</em>&nbsp;– these; <em>nityam</em>&nbsp;– as an eternal function; <em>anutiṣṭhanti</em>&nbsp;– execute regularly; <em>mānavāḥ</em>&nbsp;– human beings; <em>śraddhā-vantaḥ</em>&nbsp;– with faith and devotion; <em>anasūyantaḥ</em>&nbsp;– without envy; <em>mucyante</em>&nbsp;– become free; <em>te</em>&nbsp;– all of them; <em>api</em>&nbsp;– even; <em>karmabhiḥ</em>&nbsp;– from the bondage of the law of fruitive actions.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Those persons who execute their duties according to My injunctions and who follow this teaching faithfully, without envy, become free from the bondage of fruitive actions.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The injunction of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Kṛṣṇa, is the essence of all Vedic wisdom and therefore is eternally true without exception. As the <em>Vedas</em> are eternal, so this truth of Kṛṣṇa consciousness is also eternal. One should have ﬁrm faith in this injunction, without envying the Lord. There are many philosophers who write comments on the <em>Bhagavad-gītā</em> but have no faith in Kṛṣṇa. They will never be liberated from the bondage of fruitive action. But an ordinary man with ﬁrm faith in the eternal injunctions of the Lord, even though unable to execute such orders, becomes liberated from the bondage of the law of <em>karma.</em> In the beginning of Kṛṣṇa consciousness, one may not fully discharge the injunctions of the Lord, but because one is not resentful of this principle and works sincerely without consideration of defeat and hopelessness, he will surely be promoted to the stage of pure Kṛṣṇa consciousness.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text32" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 32</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">yae tvaetad"Byas$aUyantaAe naAnauitaï"inta mae matama, /<br />s$avaRÁaAnaivamaUX#AMstaAna, ivaiÜ" naí"Anacaetas$a: //32//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>ye tv etad abhyasūyanto<br />nānutiṣṭhanti me matam<br />sarva-jñāna-vimūḍhāṁs tān<br />viddhi naṣṭān acetasaḥ</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>ye</em>&nbsp;– those; <em>tu</em>&nbsp;– however; <em>etat</em>&nbsp;– this; <em>abhyasūyantaḥ</em>&nbsp;– out of envy; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– do not; <em>anutiṣṭhanti</em>&nbsp;– regularly perform; <em>me</em>&nbsp;– My; <em>matam</em>&nbsp;– injunction; <em>sarva-jñāna</em>&nbsp;– in all sorts of knowledge; <em>vimūḍhān</em>&nbsp;– perfectly befooled; <em>tān</em>&nbsp;– they are; <em>viddhi</em>&nbsp;– know it well; <em>naṣṭān</em>&nbsp;– all ruined; <em>acetasaḥ</em>&nbsp;– without Kṛṣṇa consciousness.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>But those who, out of envy, disregard these teachings and do not follow them regularly are to be considered bereft of all knowledge, befooled, and ruined in their endeavors for perfection.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The ﬂaw of not being Kṛṣṇa conscious is clearly stated herein. As there is punishment for disobedience to the order of the supreme executive head, so there is certainly punishment for disobedience to the order of the Supreme Personality of Godhead. A disobedient person, however great he may be, is ignorant of his own self, and of the Supreme Brahman, Paramātmā and the Personality of Godhead, due to a vacant heart. Therefore there is no hope of perfection of life for him.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text33" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 33</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">s$aä{"zAM caeí"tae svasyaA: ‘ak{(taeÁaARnavaAnaipa /<br />‘ak{(itaM yaAinta BaUtaAina inaƒah": ikM( k(ir"Syaita //33//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>sadṛśaṁ ceṣṭate svasyāḥ<br />prakṛter jñānavān api<br />prakṛtiṁ yānti bhūtāni<br />nigrahaḥ kiṁ kariṣyati</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>sadṛśam</em>&nbsp;– accordingly; <em>ceṣṭate</em>&nbsp;– tries; <em>svasyāḥ</em>&nbsp;– by his own; <em>prakṛteḥ</em>&nbsp;– modes of nature; <em>jñāna-vān</em>&nbsp;– learned; <em>api</em>&nbsp;– although; <em>prakṛtim</em>&nbsp;– nature; <em>yānti</em>&nbsp;– undergo; <em>bhūtāni</em>&nbsp;– all living entities; <em>nigrahaḥ</em>&nbsp;– repression; <em>kim</em>&nbsp;– what; <em>kariṣyati</em>&nbsp;– can do.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Even a man of knowledge acts according to his own nature, for everyone follows the nature he has acquired from the three modes. What can repression accomplish?</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">Unless one is situated on the transcendental platform of Kṛṣṇa consciousness, he cannot get free from the inﬂuence of the modes of material nature, as it is conﬁrmed by the Lord in the Seventh Chapter (7.14). Therefore, even for the most highly educated person on the mundane plane, it is impossible to get out of the entanglement of <em>māyā</em> simply by theoretical knowledge, or by separating the soul from the body. There are many so-called spiritualists who outwardly pose as advanced in the science but inwardly or privately are completely under particular modes of nature which they are unable to surpass. Academically, one may be very learned, but because of his long association with material nature, he is in bondage. Kṛṣṇa consciousness helps one to get out of the material entanglement, even though one may be engaged in his prescribed duties in terms of material existence. Therefore, without being fully in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, one should not give up his occupational duties. No one should suddenly give up his prescribed duties and become a so-called <em>yogī</em> or transcendentalist artiﬁcially. It is better to be situated in one’s position and to try to attain Kṛṣṇa consciousness under superior training. Thus one may be freed from the clutches of Kṛṣṇa’s <em>māyā.</em></div>
<div class="text-number" id="text34" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 34</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">win‰"yasyaein‰"yasyaATaeR r"AgAãe"SaAE vyavaisTataAE /<br />tayaAenaR vazAmaAgAcCe$ÔaAE ÷sya pair"painTanaAE //34//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>indriyasyendriyasyārthe<br />rāga-dveṣau vyavasthitau<br />tayor na vaśam āgacchet<br />tau hy asya paripanthinau</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>indriyasya</em>&nbsp;– of the senses; <em>indriyasya arthe</em>&nbsp;– in the sense objects; <em>rāga</em>&nbsp;– attachment; <em>dveṣau</em>&nbsp;– also detachment; <em>vyavasthitau</em>&nbsp;– put under regulations; <em>tayoḥ</em>&nbsp;– of them; <em>na</em>&nbsp;– never; <em>vaśam</em>&nbsp;– control; <em>āgacchet</em>&nbsp;– one should come; <em>tau</em>&nbsp;– those; <em>hi</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>asya</em>&nbsp;– his; <em>paripanthinau</em>&nbsp;– stumbling blocks.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>There are principles to regulate attachment and aversion pertaining to the senses and their objects. One should not come under the control of such attachment and aversion, because they are stumbling blocks on the path of self-realization.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">Those who are in Kṛṣṇa consciousness are naturally reluctant to engage in material sense gratiﬁcation. But those who are not in such consciousness should follow the rules and regulations of the revealed scriptures. Unrestricted sense enjoyment is the cause of material encagement, but one who follows the rules and regulations of the revealed scriptures does not become entangled by the sense objects. For example, sex enjoyment is a necessity for the conditioned soul, and sex enjoyment is allowed under the license of marriage ties. According to scriptural injunctions, one is forbidden to engage in sex relationships with any women other than one’s wife. All other women are to be considered as one’s mother. But in spite of such injunctions, a man is still inclined to have sex relationships with other women. These propensities are to be curbed; otherwise they will be stumbling blocks on the path of self-realization. As long as the material body is there, the necessities of the material body are allowed, but under rules and regulations. And yet, we should not rely upon the control of such allowances. One has to follow those rules and regulations, unattached to them, because practice of sense gratiﬁcation under regulations may also lead one to go astray&nbsp;– as much as there is always the chance of an accident, even on the royal roads. Although they may be very carefully maintained, no one can guarantee that there will be no danger even on the safest road. The sense enjoyment spirit has been current a very long, long time, owing to material association. Therefore, in spite of regulated sense enjoyment, there is every chance of falling down; therefore any attachment for regulated sense enjoyment must also be avoided by all means. But attachment to Kṛṣṇa consciousness, or acting always in the loving service of Kṛṣṇa, detaches one from all kinds of sensory activities. Therefore, no one should try to be detached from Kṛṣṇa consciousness at any stage of life. The whole purpose of detachment from all kinds of sense attachment is ultimately to become situated on the platform of Kṛṣṇa consciousness.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text35" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 35</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">™aeyaAna, svaDamaAeR ivagAuNA: par"DamaARtsvanauiï"taAta, /<br />svaDamaeR inaDanaM ™aeya: par"DamaAeR BayaAvah": //35//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>śreyān sva-dharmo viguṇaḥ<br />para-dharmāt sv-anuṣṭhitāt<br />sva-dharme nidhanaṁ śreyaḥ<br />para-dharmo bhayāvahaḥ</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>śreyān</em>&nbsp;– far better; <em>sva-dharmaḥ</em>&nbsp;– one’s prescribed duties; <em>viguṇaḥ</em>&nbsp;– even faulty; <em>para-dharmāt</em>&nbsp;– than duties mentioned for others; <em>su-anuṣṭhitāt</em>&nbsp;– perfectly done; <em>sva-dharme</em>&nbsp;– in one’s prescribed duties; <em>nidhanam</em>&nbsp;– destruction; <em>śreyaḥ</em>&nbsp;– better; <em>para-dharmaḥ</em>&nbsp;– duties prescribed for others; <em>bhaya-āvahaḥ</em>&nbsp;– dangerous.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>It is far better to discharge one’s prescribed duties, even though faultily, than another’s duties perfectly. Destruction in the course of performing one’s own duty is better than engaging in another’s duties, for to follow another’s path is dangerous.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">One should therefore discharge his prescribed duties in full Kṛṣṇa consciousness rather than those prescribed for others. Materially, prescribed duties are duties enjoined according to one’s psychophysical condition, under the spell of the modes of material nature. Spiritual duties are as ordered by the spiritual master for the transcendental service of Kṛṣṇa. But whether material or spiritual, one should stick to his prescribed duties even up to death, rather than imitate another’s prescribed duties. Duties on the spiritual platform and duties on the material platform may be different, but the principle of following the authorized direction is always good for the performer. When one is under the spell of the modes of material nature, one should follow the prescribed rules for his particular situation and should not imitate others. For example, a <em>brāhmaṇa,</em> who is in the mode of goodness, is nonviolent, whereas a <em>kṣatriya,</em> who is in the mode of passion, is allowed to be violent. As such, for a <em>kṣatriya</em> it is better to be vanquished following the rules of violence than to imitate a <em>brāhmaṇa</em> who follows the principles of nonviolence. Everyone has to cleanse his heart by a gradual process, not abruptly. However, when one transcends the modes of material nature and is fully situated in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, he can perform anything and everything under the direction of a bona ﬁde spiritual master. In that complete stage of Kṛṣṇa consciousness, the <em>kṣatriya</em> may act as a <em>brāhmaṇa,</em> or a <em>brāhmaṇa</em> may act as a <em>kṣatriya.</em> In the transcendental stage, the distinctions of the material world do not apply. For example, Viśvāmitra was originally a <em>kṣatriya,</em> but later on he acted as a <em>brāhmaṇa,</em> whereas Paraśurāma was a <em>brāhmaṇa</em> but later on he acted as a <em>kṣatriya.</em> Being transcendentally situated, they could do so; but as long as one is on the material platform, he must perform his duties according to the modes of material nature. At the same time, he must have a full sense of Kṛṣṇa consciousness.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text36" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 36</strong></div>
<div class="dev-uvaca">@jauRna ovaAca</div>
<div class="devanagari">@Ta ke(na ‘ayau·(Ae'yaM paApaM car"ita paUç&amp;Sa: /<br />@inacC$ªaipa vaASNAeRya balaAid"va inayaAeijata: //36//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans-uvaca">arjuna uvāca</div>
<div class="sans">atha kena prayukto ’yaṁ<br />pāpaṁ carati pūruṣaḥ<br />anicchann api vārṣṇeya<br />balād iva niyojitaḥ</div>
<div class="wbw"><em>arjunaḥ uvāca</em>&nbsp;– Arjuna said; <em>atha</em>&nbsp;– then; <em>kena</em>&nbsp;– by what; <em>prayuktaḥ</em>&nbsp;– impelled; <em>ayam</em>&nbsp;– one; <em>pāpam</em>&nbsp;– sins; <em>carati</em>&nbsp;– does; <em>pūruṣaḥ</em>&nbsp;– a man; <em>anicchan</em>&nbsp;– without desiring; <em>api</em>&nbsp;– although; <em>vārṣṇeya</em>&nbsp;– O descendant of Vṛṣṇi; <em>balāt</em>&nbsp;– by force; <em>iva</em>&nbsp;– as if; <em>niyojitaḥ</em>&nbsp;– engaged.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Arjuna said: O descendant of Vṛṣṇi, by what is one impelled to sinful acts, even unwillingly, as if engaged by force?</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">A living entity, as part and parcel of the Supreme, is originally spiritual, pure, and free from all material contaminations. Therefore, by nature he is not subject to the sins of the material world. But when he is in contact with the material nature, he acts in many sinful ways without hesitation, and sometimes even against his will. As such, Arjuna’s question to Kṛṣṇa is very sanguine, as to the perverted nature of the living entities. Although the living entity sometimes does not want to act in sin, he is still forced to act. Sinful actions are not, however, impelled by the Supersoul within, but are due to another cause, as the Lord explains in the next verse.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text37" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 37</strong></div>
<div class="dev-uvaca">™aIBagAvaAnauvaAca</div>
<div class="devanagari">k(Ama WSa ‚(AeDa WSa r"jaAegAuNAs$amauà"va: /<br />mah"AzAnaAe mah"ApaApmaA ivaÜ"Yaenaimah" vaEir"NAma, //37//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans-uvaca">śrī-bhagavān uvāca</div>
<div class="sans">kāma eṣa krodha eṣa<br />rajo-guṇa-samudbhavaḥ<br />mahāśano mahā-pāpmā<br />viddhy enam iha vairiṇam</div>
<div class="wbw"><em>śri-bhagavān uvāca</em>&nbsp;– the Personality of Godhead said; <em>kāmaḥ</em>&nbsp;– lust; <em>eṣaḥ</em>&nbsp;– this; <em>krodhaḥ</em>&nbsp;– wrath; <em>eṣaḥ</em>&nbsp;– this; <em>rajaḥ-guṇa</em>&nbsp;– the mode of passion; <em>samudbhavaḥ</em>&nbsp;– born of; <em>mahā-aśanaḥ</em>&nbsp;– all-devouring; <em>mahā-pāpmā</em>&nbsp;– greatly sinful; <em>viddhi</em>&nbsp;– know; <em>enam</em>&nbsp;– this; <em>iha</em>&nbsp;– in the material world; <em>vairiṇam</em>&nbsp;– greatest enemy.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>The Supreme Personality of Godhead said: It is lust only, Arjuna, which is born of contact with the material mode of passion and later transformed into wrath, and which is the all-devouring sinful enemy of this world.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">When a living entity comes in contact with the material creation, his eternal love for Kṛṣṇa is transformed into lust, in association with the mode of passion. Or, in other words, the sense of love of God becomes transformed into lust, as milk in contact with sour tamarind is transformed into yogurt. Then again, when lust is unsatisﬁed, it turns into wrath; wrath is transformed into illusion, and illusion continues the material existence. Therefore, lust is the greatest enemy of the living entity, and it is lust only which induces the pure living entity to remain entangled in the material world. Wrath is the manifestation of the mode of ignorance; these modes exhibit themselves as wrath and other corollaries. If, therefore, the mode of passion, instead of being degraded into the mode of ignorance, is elevated to the mode of goodness by the prescribed method of living and acting, then one can be saved from the degradation of wrath by spiritual attachment.</div>
<div class="para">The Supreme Personality of Godhead expanded Himself into many for His ever-increasing spiritual bliss, and the living entities are parts and parcels of this spiritual bliss. They also have partial independence, but by misuse of their independence, when the service attitude is transformed into the propensity for sense enjoyment, they come under the sway of lust. This material creation is created by the Lord to give facility to the conditioned souls to fulﬁll these lustful propensities, and when completely bafﬂed by prolonged lustful activities, the living entities begin to inquire about their real position.</div>
<div class="para">This inquiry is the beginning of the <em>Vedānta-sūtras,</em> wherein it is said, <em>athāto brahma-jijñāsā:</em> one should inquire into the Supreme. And the Supreme is deﬁned in <em>Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam</em> as <em>janmādy asya yato ’nvayād itarataś ca,</em> or, “The origin of everything is the Supreme Brahman.” Therefore the origin of lust is also in the Supreme. If, therefore, lust is transformed into love for the Supreme, or transformed into Kṛṣṇa consciousness&nbsp;– or, in other words, desiring everything for Kṛṣṇa&nbsp;– then both lust and wrath can be spiritualized. Hanumān, the great servitor of Lord Rāma, exhibited his wrath by burning the golden city of Rāvaṇa, but by doing so he became the greatest devotee of the Lord. Here also, in <em>Bhagavad-gītā,</em> the Lord induces Arjuna to engage his wrath upon his enemies for the satisfaction of the Lord. Therefore, lust and wrath, when they are employed in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, become our friends instead of our enemies.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text38" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 38</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">DaUmaenaAi˜ayatae vai¶"yaRTaAd"zAAeR malaena ca /<br />yaTaAelbaenaAva{taAe gABaRstaTaA taenaed"maAva{tama, //38//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>dhūmenāvriyate vahnir<br />yathādarśo malena ca<br />yatholbenāvṛto garbhas<br />tathā tenedam āvṛtam</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>dhūmena</em>&nbsp;– by smoke; <em>āvriyate</em>&nbsp;– is covered; <em>vahniḥ</em>&nbsp;– ﬁre; <em>yathā</em>&nbsp;– just as; <em>ādarśaḥ</em>&nbsp;– mirror; <em>malena</em>&nbsp;– by dust; <em>ca</em>&nbsp;– also; <em>yathā</em>&nbsp;– just as; <em>ulbena</em>&nbsp;– by the womb; <em>āvṛtaḥ</em>&nbsp;– is covered; <em>garbhaḥ</em>&nbsp;– embryo; <em>tathā</em>&nbsp;– so; <em>tena</em>&nbsp;– by that lust; <em>idam</em>&nbsp;– this; <em>āvṛtam</em>&nbsp;– is covered.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>As ﬁre is covered by smoke, as a mirror is covered by dust, or as the embryo is covered by the womb, the living entity is similarly covered by different degrees of this lust.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">There are three degrees of covering of the living entity by which his pure consciousness is obscured. This covering is but lust under different manifestations like smoke in the ﬁre, dust on the mirror, and the womb about the embryo. When lust is compared to smoke, it is understood that the ﬁre of the living spark can be a little perceived. In other words, when the living entity exhibits his Kṛṣṇa consciousness slightly, he may be likened to the ﬁre covered by smoke. Although ﬁre is necessary where there is smoke, there is no overt manifestation of ﬁre in the early stage. This stage is like the beginning of Kṛṣṇa consciousness. The dust on the mirror refers to a cleansing process of the mirror of the mind by so many spiritual methods. The best process is to chant the holy names of the Lord. The embryo covered by the womb is an analogy illustrating a helpless position, for the child in the womb is so helpless that he cannot even move. This stage of living condition can be compared to that of the trees. The trees are also living entities, but they have been put in such a condition of life by such a great exhibition of lust that they are almost void of all consciousness. The covered mirror is compared to the birds and beasts, and the smoke-covered ﬁre is compared to the human being. In the form of a human being, the living entity may revive a little Kṛṣṇa consciousness, and, if he makes further development, the ﬁre of spiritual life can be kindled in the human form of life. By careful handling of the smoke in the ﬁre, ﬁre can be made to blaze. Therefore the human form of life is a chance for the living entity to escape the entanglement of material existence. In the human form of life, one can conquer the enemy, lust, by cultivation of Kṛṣṇa consciousness under able guidance.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text39" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 39</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">@Ava{taM ÁaAnamaetaena ÁaAinanaAe inatyavaEir"NAA /<br />k(Amaè&amp;paeNA k(AEntaeya äu"SpaUre"NAAnalaena ca //39//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>āvṛtaṁ jñānam etena<br />jñānino nitya-vairiṇā<br />kāma-rūpeṇa kaunteya<br />duṣpūreṇānalena ca</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>āvṛtam</em>&nbsp;– covered; <em>jñānam</em>&nbsp;– pure consciousness; <em>etena</em>&nbsp;– by this; <em>jñāninaḥ</em>&nbsp;– of the knower; <em>nitya-vairiṇā</em>&nbsp;– by the eternal enemy; <em>kāma-rūpeṇa</em>&nbsp;– in the form of lust; <em>kaunteya</em>&nbsp;– O son of Kuntī; <em>duṣpūreṇa</em>&nbsp;– never to be satisﬁed; <em>analena</em>&nbsp;– by the ﬁre; <em>ca</em>&nbsp;– also.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Thus the wise living entity’s pure consciousness becomes covered by his eternal enemy in the form of lust, which is never satisﬁed and which burns like ﬁre.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">It is said in the <em>Manu-smṛti</em> that lust cannot be satisﬁed by any amount of sense enjoyment, just as ﬁre is never extinguished by a constant supply of fuel. In the material world, the center of all activities is sex, and thus this material world is called <em>maithunya-āgāra,</em> or the shackles of sex life. In the ordinary prison house, criminals are kept within bars; similarly, the criminals who are disobedient to the laws of the Lord are shackled by sex life. Advancement of material civilization on the basis of sense gratiﬁcation means increasing the duration of the material existence of a living entity. Therefore, this lust is the symbol of ignorance by which the living entity is kept within the material world. While one enjoys sense gratiﬁcation, it may be that there is some feeling of happiness, but actually that so-called feeling of happiness is the ultimate enemy of the sense enjoyer.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text40" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 40</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">win‰"yaAiNA manaAe bauiÜ"r"syaAiDaï"Anamaucyatae /<br />WtaEivaRmaAeh"yatyaeSa ÁaAnamaAva{tya de"ih"nama, //40//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>indriyāṇi mano buddhir<br />asyādhiṣṭhānam ucyate<br />etair vimohayaty eṣa<br />jñānam āvṛtya dehinam</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>indriyāṇi</em>&nbsp;– the senses; <em>manaḥ</em>&nbsp;– the mind; <em>buddhiḥ</em>&nbsp;– the intelligence; <em>asya</em>&nbsp;– of this lust; <em>adhiṣṭhānam</em>&nbsp;– sitting place; <em>ucyate</em>&nbsp;– is called; <em>etaiḥ</em>&nbsp;– by all these; <em>vimohayati</em>&nbsp;– bewilders; <em>eṣaḥ</em>&nbsp;– this lust; <em>jñānam</em>&nbsp;– knowledge; <em>āvṛtya</em>&nbsp;– covering; <em>dehinam</em>&nbsp;– of the embodied.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>The senses, the mind and the intelligence are the sitting places of this lust. Through them lust covers the real knowledge of the living entity and bewilders him.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The enemy has captured different strategic positions in the body of the conditioned soul, and therefore Lord Kṛṣṇa is giving hints of those places, so that one who wants to conquer the enemy may know where he can be found. Mind is the center of all the activities of the senses, and thus when we hear about sense objects the mind generally becomes a reservoir of all ideas of sense gratiﬁcation; and, as a result, the mind and the senses become the repositories of lust. Next, the intelligence department becomes the capital of such lustful propensities. Intelligence is the immediate next-door neighbor of the spirit soul. Lusty intelligence inﬂuences the spirit soul to acquire the false ego and identify itself with matter, and thus with the mind and senses. The spirit soul becomes addicted to enjoying the material senses and mistakes this as true happiness. This false identiﬁcation of the spirit soul is very nicely explained in the <em>Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam</em> (10.84.13):</div>
<div class="verse-in-purp"><em>yasyātma-buddhiḥ kuṇape tri-dhātuke<br />sva-dhīḥ kalatrādiṣu bhauma ijya-dhīḥ<br />yat-tīrtha-buddhiḥ salile na karhicij<br />janeṣv abhijñeṣu sa eva go-kharaḥ</em></div>
<div class="purp">“A human being who identiﬁes this body made of three elements with his self, who considers the by-products of the body to be his kinsmen, who considers the land of birth worshipable, and who goes to the place of pilgrimage simply to take a bath rather than meet men of transcendental knowledge there is to be considered like an ass or a cow.”</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text41" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 41</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">tasmaAÔvaimain‰"yaANyaAd"AE inayamya Bar"taSaRBa /<br />paApmaAnaM ‘ajaih" ÷enaM ÁaAnaivaÁaAnanaAzAnama, //41//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>tasmāt tvam indriyāṇy ādau<br />niyamya bharatarṣabha<br />pāpmānaṁ prajahi hy enaṁ<br />jñāna-vijñāna-nāśanam</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>tasmāt</em>&nbsp;– therefore; <em>tvam</em>&nbsp;– you; <em>indriyāṇi</em>&nbsp;– senses; <em>ādau</em>&nbsp;– in the beginning; <em>niyamya</em>&nbsp;– by regulating; <em>bharata-ṛṣabha</em>&nbsp;– O chief amongst the descendants of Bharata; <em>pāpmānam</em>&nbsp;– the great symbol of sin; <em>prajahi</em>&nbsp;– curb; <em>hi</em>&nbsp;– certainly; <em>enam</em>&nbsp;– this; <em>jñāna</em>&nbsp;– of knowledge; <em>vijñāna</em>&nbsp;– and scientiﬁc knowledge of the pure soul; <em>nāśanam</em>&nbsp;– the destroyer.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Therefore, O Arjuna, best of the Bhāratas, in the very beginning curb this great symbol of sin [lust] by regulating the senses, and slay this destroyer of knowledge and self-realization.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The Lord advised Arjuna to regulate the senses from the very beginning so that he could curb the greatest sinful enemy, lust, which destroys the urge for self-realization and speciﬁc knowledge of the self. <em>Jñāna</em> refers to knowledge of self as distinguished from non-self, or in other words, knowledge that the spirit soul is not the body. <em>Vijñāna</em> refers to speciﬁc knowledge of the spirit soul’s constitutional position and his relationship to the Supreme Soul. It is explained thus in the <em>Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam</em> (2.9.31):</div>
<div class="verse-in-purp"><em>jñānaṁ parama-guhyaṁ me<br />yad vijñāna-samanvitam<br />sa-rahasyaṁ tad-aṅgaṁ ca<br />gṛhāṇa gaditaṁ mayā</em></div>
<div class="purp">“The knowledge of the self and Supreme Self is very conﬁdential and mysterious, but such knowledge and speciﬁc realization can be understood if explained with their various aspects by the Lord Himself.” <em>Bhagavad-gītā</em> gives us that general and speciﬁc knowledge of the self. The living entities are parts and parcels of the Lord, and therefore they are simply meant to serve the Lord. This consciousness is called Kṛṣṇa consciousness. So, from the very beginning of life one has to learn this Kṛṣṇa consciousness, and thereby one may become fully Kṛṣṇa conscious and act accordingly.</div>
<div class="para">Lust is only the perverted reﬂection of the love of God which is natural for every living entity. But if one is educated in Kṛṣṇa consciousness from the very beginning, that natural love of God cannot deteriorate into lust. When love of God deteriorates into lust, it is very difﬁcult to return to the normal condition. Nonetheless, Kṛṣṇa consciousness is so powerful that even a late beginner can become a lover of God by following the regulative principles of devotional service. So, from any stage of life, or from the time of understanding its urgency, one can begin regulating the senses in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, devotional service of the Lord, and turn the lust into love of Godhead&nbsp;– the highest perfectional stage of human life.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text42" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 42</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">win‰"yaAiNA par"ANyaAò"ir"in‰"yaeBya: parM" mana: /<br />manas$astau par"A bauiÜ"yaAeR bauÜe": par"tastau s$a: //42//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>indriyāṇi parāṇy āhur<br />indriyebhyaḥ paraṁ manaḥ<br />manasas tu parā buddhir<br />yo buddheḥ paratas tu saḥ</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>indriyāṇi</em>&nbsp;– senses; <em>parāṇi</em>&nbsp;– superior; <em>āhuḥ</em>&nbsp;– are said; <em>indriyebhyaḥ</em>&nbsp;– more than the senses; <em>param</em>&nbsp;– superior; <em>manaḥ</em>&nbsp;– the mind; <em>manasaḥ</em>&nbsp;– more than the mind; <em>tu</em>&nbsp;– also; <em>parā</em>&nbsp;– superior; <em>buddhiḥ</em>&nbsp;– intelligence; <em>yaḥ</em>&nbsp;– who; <em>buddheḥ</em>&nbsp;– more than the intelligence; <em>parataḥ</em>&nbsp;– superior; <em>tu</em>&nbsp;– but; <em>saḥ</em>&nbsp;– he.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>The working senses are superior to dull matter; mind is higher than the senses; intelligence is still higher than the mind; and he [the soul] is even higher than the intelligence.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">The senses are different outlets for the activities of lust. Lust is reserved within the body, but it is given vent through the senses. Therefore, the senses are superior to the body as a whole. These outlets are not in use when there is superior consciousness, or Kṛṣṇa consciousness. In Kṛṣṇa consciousness the soul makes direct connection with the Supreme Personality of Godhead; therefore the hierarchy of bodily functions, as described here, ultimately ends in the Supreme Soul. Bodily action means the functions of the senses, and stopping the senses means stopping all bodily actions. But since the mind is active, then even though the body may be silent and at rest, the mind will act&nbsp;– as it does during dreaming. But above the mind is the determination of the intelligence, and above the intelligence is the soul proper. If, therefore, the soul is directly engaged with the Supreme, naturally all other subordinates, namely, the intelligence, mind and senses, will be automatically engaged. In the <em>Kaṭha Upaniṣad</em> there is a similar passage, in which it is said that the objects of sense gratiﬁcation are superior to the senses, and mind is superior to the sense objects. If, therefore, the mind is directly engaged in the service of the Lord constantly, then there is no chance that the senses will become engaged in other ways. This mental attitude has already been explained. <em>Paraṁ dṛṣṭvā nivartate.</em> If the mind is engaged in the transcendental service of the Lord, there is no chance of its being engaged in the lower propensities. In the <em>Kaṭha Upaniṣad</em> the soul has been described as <em>mahān,</em> the great. Therefore the soul is above all&nbsp;– namely, the sense objects, the senses, the mind and the intelligence. Therefore, directly understanding the constitutional position of the soul is the solution of the whole problem.</div>
<div class="para">With intelligence one has to seek out the constitutional position of the soul and then engage the mind always in Kṛṣṇa consciousness. That solves the whole problem. A neophyte spiritualist is generally advised to keep aloof from the objects of the senses. But aside from that, one has to strengthen the mind by use of intelligence. If by intelligence one engages one’s mind in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, by complete surrender unto the Supreme Personality of Godhead, then, automatically, the mind becomes stronger, and even though the senses are very strong, like serpents, they will be no more effective than serpents with broken fangs. But even though the soul is the master of intelligence and mind, and the senses also, still, unless it is strengthened by association with Kṛṣṇa in Kṛṣṇa consciousness, there is every chance of falling down due to the agitated mind.</div>
<div class="text-number" id="text43" ></div>
<div class="text"><strong>TEXT 43</strong></div>
<div class="devanagari">WvaM bauÜe": parM" bauä,"DvaA s$aMstaByaAtmaAnamaAtmanaA /<br />jaih" zA‡auM mah"AbaAh"Ae k(Amaè&amp;paM äu"r"As$ad"ma, //43//</div>
<div class="special"> </div>
<div class="sans"><em>evaṁ buddheḥ paraṁ buddhvā<br />saṁstabhyātmānam ātmanā<br />jahi śatruṁ mahā-bāho<br />kāma-rūpaṁ durāsadam</em></div>
<div class="wbw"><em>evam</em>&nbsp;– thus; <em>buddheḥ</em>&nbsp;– to intelligence; <em>param</em>&nbsp;– superior; <em>buddhvā</em>&nbsp;– knowing; <em>saṁstabhya</em>&nbsp;– by steadying; <em>ātmānam</em>&nbsp;– the mind; <em>ātmanā</em>&nbsp;– by deliberate intelligence; <em>jahi</em>&nbsp;– conquer; <em>śatrum</em>&nbsp;– the enemy; <em>mahā-bāho</em>&nbsp;– O mighty-armed one; <em>kāma-rūpam</em>&nbsp;– in the form of lust; <em>durāsadam</em>&nbsp;– formidable.</div>
<div class="trans-title">TRANSLATION</div>
<div class="trans"><strong>Thus knowing oneself to be transcendental to the material senses, mind and intelligence, O mighty-armed Arjuna, one should steady the mind by deliberate spiritual intelligence [Kṛṣṇa consciousness] and thus&nbsp;– by spiritual strength&nbsp;– conquer this insatiable enemy known as lust.</strong></div>
<div class="purp-title">PURPORT</div>
<div class="para-no-indent">This Third Chapter of the <em>Bhagavad-gītā</em> is conclusively directive to Kṛṣṇa consciousness by knowing oneself as the eternal servitor of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, without considering impersonal voidness the ultimate end. In the material existence of life, one is certainly inﬂuenced by propensities for lust and desire for dominating the resources of material nature. Desire for overlording and for sense gratiﬁcation is the greatest enemy of the conditioned soul; but by the strength of Kṛṣṇa consciousness, one can control the material senses, the mind and the intelligence. One may not give up work and prescribed duties all of a sudden; but by gradually developing Kṛṣṇa consciousness, one can be situated in a transcendental position without being inﬂuenced by the material senses and the mind&nbsp;– by steady intelligence directed toward one’s pure identity. This is the sum total of this chapter. In the immature stage of material existence, philosophical speculations and artiﬁcial attempts to control the senses by the so-called practice of yogic postures can never help a man toward spiritual life. He must be trained in Kṛṣṇa consciousness by higher intelligence.</div>
<div class="ch-end"><em>Thus end the Bhaktivedanta Purports to the Third Chapter of the</em> Śrīmad Bhagavad-gītā <em>in the matter of </em>Karma-yoga, <em>or the Discharge of One’s Prescribed Duty in Kṛṣṇa Consciousness.</em></div>
</body>
</html>